<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Forest Garden Wales Blog</title>
    <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Forest Garden Wales</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <managingEditor>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</webMaster>
    <copyright>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Weeding forest garden style</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/weeding-forest-garden-style/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 09:57:03 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/weeding-forest-garden-style/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;The “chop ’n‘ drop” method of mulching applies equally to weeding in the forest garden&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1861/44068045164_d01e556dd0_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Weeded plants on a bark mulch&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Some call the look scruffy, I call it efficient&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;In the chapter on Maintenance in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.agroforestry.co.uk/product/creating-a-forest-garden-2/&#34;&gt;Creating a Forest Garden&lt;/a&gt;, Martin Crawford says&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I very rarely dig up weeds… instead I just chop them off at soil level&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the damp weeks that followed the summer’s drought, there was a lot of growth and a lot of weeding. The mineral accumulating &lt;a href=&#34;https://pfaf.org/USER/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Rumex+obtusifolius&#34;&gt;docks&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://pfaf.org/user/plant.aspx?LatinName=Taraxacum+officinale&#34;&gt;dandelions&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://pfaf.org/user/plant.aspx?LatinName=Plantago+lanceolata&#34;&gt;plantains&lt;/a&gt; were cut and left to compost in situ. This is in much the same way as you “chop ’n‘ drop” &lt;a href=&#34;https://pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Symphytum+uplandicum&#34;&gt;comfrey&lt;/a&gt; under fruit trees. Just imagine, no wheelbarrow, no compost heap, much less bother 🙂&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A forest garden is a way to garden</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/forest-garden-is-way-to-garden/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2018 15:16:26 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/forest-garden-is-way-to-garden/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;After listening to a @margaretroach podcast &amp; reading a @DaveGoulson book, I realised that I don’t need to worry about plants!&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/959/41405332295_4e395dcfa9_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pale pink Quince blossom in the low evening sun&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;A quince tree, part of the canopy layer. Choosing other plants has been more challenging.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;I listened to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/margaretroach&#34;&gt;Margaret Roach&lt;/a&gt; podcast &lt;a href=&#34;https://awaytogarden.com/&#34;&gt;A Way to Garden&lt;/a&gt;, the episode entitled &lt;a href=&#34;https://awaytogarden.com/go-ahead-we-dare-you-widen-your-plant-palette-with-andy-brand/&#34;&gt;“Go ahead, we dare you: widen your plant palette”&lt;/a&gt;, with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.instagram.com/andyjbrand/&#34;&gt;Andy Brand&lt;/a&gt;. A renowned plantsperson, he moved to a new job in a new area and was confronted with an array of new plants. In some ways, I can relate to that feeling as I’ve only been gardening in earnest for 3 years. And there is just &lt;strong&gt;so much to learn&lt;/strong&gt;!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forest gardening is an inbetweeny sort of gardening, as it concentrates on the produce and wildlife side of things. In some respects, that makes it easier, as the plant palette for the tree canopy layer is relatively limited. It’s a functional and productive way to garden. I drew up a list of trees and harvests that I wanted, jiggled them around on the plan, bought them and planted them (sounds so easy in retrospect!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I’ve also finished the majority of the ground cover planting, I’m looking at the shrub layer, herbaceous perennials and what are sometimes called “system plants”. System plants don’t have a direct harvest but benefit the ecosystem of the garden. Examples include nitrogen fixers, mineral accumulators, pollinator friendly flowers and predator friendly plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where the fun &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; starts, because this is where you can play with the human-eye-pleasing shapes and colours. This is also where I feel most out of my depth – this is the realms of Traditional Gardening [sic]; thousands of varieties, a million combinations. I don’t really care what a quince tree looks like, it just has an innate beauty. But faced with a choice, and making aesthetic and visually oriented design decisions, that’s a whole new ball game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, help is at hand. I’m in the middle of reading &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18465526-a-sting-in-the-tale&#34;&gt;A Sting in the Tale&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://mobile.twitter.com/DaveGoulson&#34;&gt;Dave Goulson&lt;/a&gt; (recommended by &lt;a href=&#34;https://mobile.twitter.com/wuthering_alice&#34;&gt;Steph&lt;/a&gt;). It is a right-rollicking and eye-opening read about the lives and loves of bumblebees. I am making mental notes about bee friendly plants, and then cross-referencing that with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.agroforestry.co.uk/about_us/&#34;&gt;Martin Crawford&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.agroforestry.co.uk/product/creating-a-forest-garden-2/&#34;&gt;Creating a Forest Garden&lt;/a&gt;. He has a whole appendix entitled “Plants to attract beneficial insects and bees”, with tables of data about flowering times and the like. I’m cross referencing that with the excellent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.joyofplants.com/iphone.php&#34;&gt;Joy of Plants&lt;/a&gt; app to get the low down on dimensions, foliage and colours, and drawing up a shortlist of favourites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, I am following the insects for my choice of plants. I am even considering heather, it is that radical an approach. (I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; don’t like heather &lt;strong&gt;but&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rhs.org.uk/Plants/100113/i-Erica-carnea-i-Nathalie/Details&#34;&gt;Erica carnea&lt;/a&gt; is a good source of nectar and pollen and is in flower January to April.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll write a follow-up on my choice of flowers for a forest garden with some cheery photos 🙂&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When you are dying, surround yourself with life</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/when-you-are-dying/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2018 11:44:15 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/when-you-are-dying/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;@doctor_oxford’s article on palliative care and nature struck a chord with my own experiences&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1868/29680293497_e084079070_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Closeup of white Rosa rugosa flower with bumblebee in centre&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;White Rosa rugosa flower, and bumblebee, both very alive&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;Dr Rachel Clarke &lt;a href=&#34;https://mobile.twitter.com/doctor_oxford&#34;&gt;@doctor_oxford&lt;/a&gt;, palliative care doctor and author, has written a beautiful piece in the New York Times called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/09/08/opinion/sunday/nhs-hospice.html&#34;&gt;In Life’s Last Moments, Open a Window&lt;/a&gt;. It’s about her hospice patients and the importance of nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My brother died of cancer in June 2006. A few weeks before he died, he spent many hours in my Mum’s garden, taking photographs of all the flowers in great and meticulous detail. I meant to post some of the photos but I can’t find them, so they are just a memory for now, as opposed to photons from life on the flypaper of photography. This is a good thing, it helps emphasise the fragile impermenance of every thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I learnt from that difficult time is that the most important thing is &lt;strong&gt;being&lt;/strong&gt; with someone, something, somewhere. And being with nature is being alive and present and vital. As we are all dying, some unfortunately faster than others, please take the time to enjoy your gardens and each other, and surround yourself with life.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I’ve had enough, it’s time to quit!</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/time-to-quit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Aug 2018 11:33:27 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/time-to-quit/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Sometimes, failure is the best option&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1845/43356338845_f173422d61_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Big clouds behind row of trees, telephone line and small green hedge&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Full steam ahead #ForestGarden!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;For the past 3 years I’ve been leading a double life. By day, a jolly Forest Gardener. By night, a geeky web designer. After moving to Wales, I always thought I would be able to combine both roles, with the odd bit of remote working for building websites to offset the labour-intensive setting up a forest garden. But I was wrong, my skills (accessible HTML &amp;amp; modular CSS if you were wondering) are too niche for part-time work. So, it’s time to quit!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a leap into the unknown. From next May, I will be a running 1-day forest garden course and half-day tours each month, and I’ll have to make a living from it. This means at least half a dozen people on each course &amp;amp; tour. Eek.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this autumn &amp;amp; winter I will be re-launching the website and creating a series of short videos, outlining the course. As well as finishing the forest garden, fitting rabbit-proof fencing and starting the Ornamental Maintenance-free Forest Garden (OMFG!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does mean more blogging (thank you for the impetus, oh &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/gdnbloggers&#34;&gt;#GdnBloggers&lt;/a&gt;!!) and rather awkward self-promotion on all them social networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll still be available for web design work, doing my bit to combat digital feudalism with my &lt;em&gt;incredibly&lt;/em&gt; fast website starter kit, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.indiego.org.uk/&#34;&gt;Indiego&lt;/a&gt;. So, if you like social justice and want a fast website, drop me a line &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:hello@growdigital.org&#34;&gt;hello@growdigital.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nettle soup</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/nettle-soup/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jul 2018 10:45:51 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/nettle-soup/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Stalwart recipe of the foraging community&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1882/42746778580_b0866baaea_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bowl of nettle soup with creme fraiche&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Nettle soup, by Leslie Seaton from Seattle, WA, USA&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;h2 id=&#34;ingredients&#34;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;½ carrier bag stinging nettle tops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;50g vegan margarine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 large onion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 litre vegetable stock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 large potato, peeled &amp;amp; cut into cubes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 large carrot, peeled &amp;amp; chopped&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salt &amp;amp; pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 tbsp Oatly creme fraiche&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;method&#34;&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wash nettles, get rid of thick stalks, drain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Melt vegan margarine in large saucepan, add onion, cook gently 5-7 minutes until softened&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add stock, nettles, potato &amp;amp; carrot. Bring to simmer, cook gently until potato soft, about 15 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove from heat, purée with electric hand-held blender &amp;amp; season with salt &amp;amp; pepper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Serve with tablespoonful of creme fraiche on top, can also add swirl of olive oil &amp;amp; Tabasco sauce.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Lure of the Stinging-less Nettle</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/the-lure-of-the-stinging-less-nettle/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jul 2018 16:09:44 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/the-lure-of-the-stinging-less-nettle/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;A long time ago I heard about the legend of The Stinging-less Netlle, a fabled plant with all of the nitrogen-rich, low-maintenance and nutritional benefits of the stinging nettle without any of the stinging.&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/839/43399566341_3e9c75140c_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Close up of nettle, with flowers and slightly curled leaves&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;The Stinging-less Nettle, Urtica dioica subsp. galeopsifolia, photo by Wicken Fen National Trust Reserve&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;The stinging nettle &lt;a href=&#34;https://pfaf.org/User/plant.aspx?LatinName=Urtica+dioica&#34;&gt;Urtica dioica&lt;/a&gt; is an excellent forest garden plant. Before it flowers*, it makes a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/nettle-soup/&#34;&gt;fantastic soup&lt;/a&gt;, an excellent if strong-tasting spinach replacement, it makes &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/wordofmouth/2011/may/18/homebrew-from-the-hedgerow&#34;&gt;a nice beer&lt;/a&gt;, it contains &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Urtica_dioica#Food&#34;&gt;buckets of iron&lt;/a&gt;, oodles of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gardenersworld.com/how-to/maintain-the-garden/how-to-make-a-nettle-feed/&#34;&gt;nitrogen&lt;/a&gt;, it can be used as a nutritious &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gardenmyths.com/composting-the-cut-and-drop-method/&#34;&gt;chop ‘n’ drop&lt;/a&gt; mulching material or made into a fertiliser tea, it’s the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Urtica_dioica#Ecology&#34;&gt;main food for many butterflies&lt;/a&gt; and a host of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wildlifetrusts.org/wildlife-explorer/wildflowers/stinging-nettle&#34;&gt;other wildlife&lt;/a&gt;, it’s easy to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, what’s not to love? 😍&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh. The sting. I always sting myself when collecting stinging nettles, no matter how long my gloves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it weren’t for the sting, we’d all be growing it [intentionally] in our gardens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had heard of a stinging-less sub-species, and thanks to the workings of the wonderful web, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nationaltrust.org.uk/wicken-fen-nature-reserve&#34;&gt;Wicken Fen National Trust Reserve&lt;/a&gt; confirmed its very real existence in a tweet &lt;a href=&#34;https://mobile.twitter.com/WickenFenNT/status/1015335041692585984&#34;&gt;@WickenFenNT&lt;/a&gt;. It’s scientific name is Urtica dioica subsp. galeopsifolia and a common name is Fen Nettle, and I also found it on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ispotnature.org/communities/uk-and-ireland/view/observation/541738/wicken-fen-4&#34;&gt;iSpot nature website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, perennial vegetable suppliers &lt;a href=&#34;https://backyardlarder.co.uk&#34;&gt;Backyard Larder&lt;/a&gt; said that they’re &lt;a href=&#34;https://mobile.twitter.com/BackyardLarder/status/1017793141003423744&#34;&gt;planning a trip&lt;/a&gt; to Wicken Fen and will ask about seed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am very excited about the prospect of a stinging-less nettle bed, effortless spring soups and nutritious summer mulching and I’m sure you should be able to treat as a cut-again crop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;*After it has flowered, apparently there is a build up in gritty particles called cysoliths, which can damage the kidneys if ingested.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vegan banana cake</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/vegan-banana-cake/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 11:51:04 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/vegan-banana-cake/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Very easy vegan banana cake, which I topped with our first ever gooseberries (Hinnomaki Red)!&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/847/43255228442_b2da5fde84_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cake with fruity topping in tin&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Vegan banana cake topped with part-cooked gooseberries&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;We picked our first ever gooseberries last week. I washed them, popped them into a saucepan with a tiny bit of water, cooked them on a low heat for a few minutes until soft then added some sugar. I then put this on the top of banana cake just before it went in the oven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ingredients&#34;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 bananas (ripe)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;75g coconut oil (melted or at least softened)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;140g sugar (raw if you have it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;80g almond milk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tbsp vanilla extract&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 flax egg (1 tbsp ground flax seed dissolved in water)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;½ tsp baking soda&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1½ tsp baking powder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 tsp cinnamon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pinch sea salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;240g whole wheat flour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;method&#34;&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 180°C.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix flax seed with 3 tbsp water and set aside.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a medium bowl, use a fork to mash the bananas with coconut oil and sugar, mix well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add flaxseeds, vanilla and milk, mix well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a separate bowl, combine dry ingredients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the dry mix to the wet and stir until just combined, do not over mix. Pour batter into tin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bake for 25-30 minutes or until a toothpick can be inserted and removed cleanly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/920/28497204027_358a109d32_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Square cake sliced on cooling rack, red fruit on top, piece missing&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Vegana banana cake topped with gooseberry with, er, a piece missing already…&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recipe adapated from &lt;a href=&#34;https://fortheloveofleaves.blogspot.co.uk/2013/04/vegan-banana-cake.html&#34;&gt;For the Love of Leaves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a Forest Garden?</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/what-is-a-forest-garden/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jul 2018 09:36:44 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/what-is-a-forest-garden/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;A simple definition of what makes a #ForestGarden tl;dr productive, self-sustaining and low maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1768/42913617132_79f71b8244_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Line drawing of tall tree next to medium tree next to spiky shrub in profile, ground cover on the ground&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;The multi-layered nature of a Forest Garden illustrated&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;I gave another &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forestgarden.wales/talks/intro/&#34;&gt;Introduction to Forest Gardening&lt;/a&gt; talk the other day (press &lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt; to see the notes), and I rejigged my definition of a forest garden:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Productive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-sustaining&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low maintenance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-productive&#34;&gt;1. Productive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A forest garden is a productive garden, growing food and wood crops.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is multi-layered, using all available space in 3 dimensions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-self-sustaining&#34;&gt;2. Self-sustaining&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A forest garden is designed to be a self-contained and self-regulating system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It supplies its own nutrients with mineral accumulators and nitrogen fixing plants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a balanced eco-system, the predators naturally keep the pests in check.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-low-maintenance&#34;&gt;3. Low maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No watering (all water on-site)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimal weeding (permanent living ground cover)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No digging (mostly perennials with some self-seeding annuals)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No fertilisers (fertility from mineral accumulators and nitrogen fixers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No compost (compost in-situ)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book I always recommend is Martin Crawford’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.agroforestry.co.uk/product/creating-a-forest-garden-2/&#34;&gt;Creating a Forest Garden&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vegan Chocolate Brownies</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/vegan-chocolate-brownies/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 10:41:22 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/vegan-chocolate-brownies/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;A recipe for the kind of world famous cakes you can expect on our #ForestGarden tour! &lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/896/42957769501_35aa0fd5f5_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Plate piled high with chocolate brownies&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Delicious, moist, very chocolatey vegan chocolate brownies, this batch with nuts and sultanas&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;h2 id=&#34;ingredients&#34;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;250g plain flour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;350g demerara sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;65g plain cocoa powder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tsp baking powder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tsp salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;250ml water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;250ml vegetable oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tsp vanilla extract&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;method&#34;&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preheat the oven to 180°C&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a large bowl, stir together the flour, sugar, cocoa powder, baking powder and salt. Pour in water, vegetable oil and vanilla; mix until well blended. Spread evenly in a 23 x 33cm baking tin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bake for 25 to 30 minutes in the preheated oven, until the top is no longer shiny. Let cool for at least 10 minutes before cutting into squares.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;variation&#34;&gt;Variation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add grated zest of an orange, substitute some of the water with the orange juice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add nuts, dried fruit etc. as is your wont.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://allrecipes.co.uk/recipe/6036/vegan-brownies.aspx&#34;&gt;http://allrecipes.co.uk/recipe/6036/vegan-brownies.aspx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photographs from the Permaculture Tywi forest garden tour</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/forest-garden-tour-permaculture-tywi-photos/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 09:36:51 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/forest-garden-tour-permaculture-tywi-photos/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Photographs of the @permatywi visit to #ForestGarden Wales, by Christine Jones&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/917/43060641451_c14e17e2a4_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Man in hat with pouch (not paunch) standing in the long grass, talking with a circling group of permaculturalists, polytunnel, house and hills in the background.&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Permaculture Tywi group tour of Forest Garden Wales. Jake is standing by the Hovenia dulcis (raisin tree) in the Accidental Meadow. The disembodied leg in the foreground belongs to permaculture teacher Paul Jennings.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/permatywi&#34;&gt;Permaculture Tywi&lt;/a&gt;, a permaculture group from the Tywi Valley in Wales, came on a magnificent forest garden tour on Saturday 23rd June, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/permaculture-tywi-tour/&#34;&gt;as previously reported&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m very lucky that Christine Jones and others took photographs – I keep meaning to but I find myself too busy talking. Thought it would be nice to share some of the photos. Apologies, I didn’t get everyone’s name so I can’t caption them properly!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1829/42143351375_07791f6181_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Misty, mature trees in background, young trees and long grass in foreground&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Forest Garden One (as it’s affectionately known) first thing in the morning, before the tour starts. Photo by Jake.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1802/41233215460_917a3c514d_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Two people walking up to polytunnel past long grass, man in hat talking, white dog to the right, mature trees in the background&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The polytunnel in the forest garden&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1769/42993829402_beb7b9ea5e_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Hedge up hill to left, long grass in foreground, mature trees in background, polytunnel middle distance to right, small white dog walking up hedge path&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The area which one day will become the Potting Shed&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/837/28174656327_9cc0d0065e_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Shaped garden, two beds with bark mulch, on a slope, two people looking on, electricity pole, trees and hills in background&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The Boozey Herb Garden, two beds planted and mulched with bark, small olive tree in the middle&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1828/28174654637_1b108fda97_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Work area inside polytunnel, desks and shelves stacked with pots&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The potting area inside the polytunnel&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/836/28174650487_e1bc07312f_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Inside of polytunnel, lots of crops&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Rare interior shot of the polytunnel – ground cherry front left, chillies front right (perennial Locoto chilli doing best), then tomatillos, and climbing achocha. See The Real Seed Catalogue for more details&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/844/29171954728_113a615046_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;3 bay compost bins made out of pallets, propagation bed in foreground rather swamped with alefoot plant&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The rather underused compost bays by the polytunnel, with a propagation bed stacked with very happy Glechoma hederacea (Alefoot or False Ivy), and some flowering Valeriana officinalis. The Alefoot showing what a good ground cover plant looks like!&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/915/42324668894_933d3dc883_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Group of people around raised bed by polytunnel and compost bins&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Jake talking about alefoot and the importance of propagation beds&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/913/41233210120_7b2c5c7a77_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Man pointing at strawberry plants in raised bed, next to a towering purple flowered foxglove&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Jake showing how you are supposed to propagate strawberries, using individual pots for the runners. Quite often I’ll let the runners roots naturally before planting them out, depending on time&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1824/42993811082_bf381b4c0e_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Group of people by a bed with mature trees in background&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Jake talking about the magical Fruit Triangle, where soft fruit just disappears without explanation (I blame the birds…)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1762/42324665124_1892cbd51f_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Small fruit bushes in foreground, poytunnel middle distance, trees and hills beyond&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The world famous Fruit Triangle doing it’s fruity thing&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1766/42141134465_ca0f57e03c_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Photo of meadow to left, bushy green young hedge to right, polytunnel at end of the path, trees and hills in the background&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The glorious West Wales countryside viewable over the polytunnel. To the left is the Orchard with the Accidental Mini-Meadow, to the right is the Cornus stolonifera windbreak hedge. I like Cornus (dogwood), as it’s less floppy than Rosa rugosa and easier to manage.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/918/42324660084_571985e7fc_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Long young hedge to left, sheet mulched with woven plastic, grass path and people to the right&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The North Face windbreak hedge of Juneberry, Guelder Rose and Sea Buckthorn. Permaculture teacher Paul Jennings is catching 40 winks in the midst of a rather busy day&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/917/29171948068_674a0d374d_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Curved grass path in centre, long grass to the right, sheet mulched area to the left, mature trees in backgorund&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Sheet mulch vs. Meadow – I would do things differently but then, who wouldn’t? In the future, I’ll be far more selective with when I sheet mulch an area, ie just before I need it. In the meantime, keep it as long grass, so that the soil and wildlife benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1805/43043439651_4ff08d111c_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Plastic sheet mulched area, weighted down with bits of wood&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The rather unglamourous Farside area, still under heavy development. I planted canopy trees (sweet chestnut, cherry, crab apple etc) but would have kept a grass understory until ready to plant out ground cover.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1810/29171974858_055a5873e3_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Grass path with mature trees and electricity pole to left, sheet mulched area and young willow coppice to right&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The far reaches of the eastern end of the forest garden. This the rather neglected Willow Coppice, which will be used for wood chip mulch in the short term and possibly weaving in the longer term&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1825/42993817972_5c269d40c8_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Man with hat lifting up sheet mulch to show bare soil beneath&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Jake showing the condition of the soil after the sheet mulch is pulled up, and then covered with mulch&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/847/42993817112_1c50c0a584_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Raised beds with bean poles, polytunnel to left, people walking down from the right&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;It’s okay to have annual raised beds in a forest garden 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos copyright Christine Jones, and possibly others.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Permaculture Tywi forest garden tour</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/permaculture-tywi-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 13:37:21 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/permaculture-tywi-tour/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;@PermaTywi came for a #ForestGarden tour on Saturday, about a dozen, everyone seemed to enjoy themselves!&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/896/42957769501_35aa0fd5f5_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chocolate brownies on a white plate&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Not forest garden at all really but the vegan chocolate brownies went down well&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/permatywi&#34;&gt;Permaculture Tywi&lt;/a&gt; from Llandeilo way (the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/River_Tywi&#34;&gt;Tywi Valley&lt;/a&gt;) came for a #ForestGarden tour last Saturday. It formed part of their &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.permaculture.co.uk/courses&#34;&gt;Permaculture Design Course&lt;/a&gt;, so I created a bespoke &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forestgarden.wales/talks/tywi/&#34;&gt;Introduction to Forest Gardening&lt;/a&gt; talk for them. Of course, I spelt Tywi wrong! On the plus side, the course leader Paul Jennings told us about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Straight-tusked_elephant&#34;&gt;straight tusked elephant&lt;/a&gt; and the pivotal role it used played in the ecology. So, my not-haiku became:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gently balance the garden
On the cusp of woodland
With minimal elephant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk went down well I think, although I do try to squeeze everything in to an hour, so it inevitably bursts the seams of time and spills into an hour and a half. Luckily, people had fuelled up on the famous &lt;a href=&#34;http://simp.ly/publish/L624C8&#34;&gt;vegan chocolate brownies&lt;/a&gt; (pictured).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the great things with talking about what you’ve learned is that you receive more ideas and inspirations in return. One chap mentioned non-woven geotextile mulch as an alternative to woven sheet mulch, Paul Jennings talked about cut and drop mulching, Chris used to be a garden designer and has inspired me to find out more about surveying methods and CAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a privilege to share knowledge with such an interesting and engaged group of invdividuals 🙂.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7 Magical Things about Forest Gardens</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/7-magical-things/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2018 21:19:15 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/7-magical-things/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;With @GWandShows highlighting the benefits of #meadows, rain gardens &amp; #plasticfree, have a look at the magic a #ForestGarden can provide 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1731/41717565655_a6ba026741_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hover fly on pale pink composite flower&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Hover fly on Valeriana officinalis in the Forest Garden Wales propagation bed&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/talks/magic/#1&#34;&gt;gave a talk&lt;/a&gt; recently to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drefachfelindregardeningclub.co.uk/&#34;&gt;local gardening club&lt;/a&gt; and I wanted to highlight the benefits of a forest garden in an accessible way (if you didn’t know, a forest garden is a productive way to garden using trees, shrubs and perennial plants). So here are my top 7 magical things that you may find hard to believe:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zero watering&lt;/strong&gt;: No, really. If you have an established forest garden, you don’t have to water it. Obviously, your seedlings, annual veg and pots will still need that watering can &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;TLC&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minimal mowing&lt;/strong&gt;: There are no lawns in a forest garden (unless you want one!!), which only leaves grass paths. For larger areas of grass, create your own mini-meadow, mow paths through them and bring out the scythe once or twice a year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Occasional weeding&lt;/strong&gt;: Everything is mulched in a forest garden, whether with ground cover plants, temporary green manures or “cut ‘n’ drop” comfrey. Weeds find it very hard to get established.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No dig&lt;/strong&gt;: The soil in a forest garden is &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; covered and mineral accumulators like comfrey are incorporated into the design, and with the vast majority of plants being perennial, the underground network of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mycorrhiza&#34;&gt;mycorrhizal fungi&lt;/a&gt; has a chance to get established. Apart from the initial planting, there is next to no digging (though it won’t feel like it after you’ve planted a hundred bare-root whips for your windbreak…)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No chemicals&lt;/strong&gt;: The aim of a forest garden is to &lt;strong&gt;work with nature&lt;/strong&gt;, which means creating a &lt;em&gt;healthy balance&lt;/em&gt; in the garden. By encouraging predators, pollinators and a healthy soil, there really isn’t any need for chemicals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wildlife haven&lt;/strong&gt;: With no chemicals, in-situ composting and a multi-layered use of the garden space, wildlife has a home and a food supply, all the way up to the top of the chain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abundant produce!&lt;/strong&gt;: A forest garden is a &lt;strong&gt;productive space&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s like an orchard, combined with a perennial vegetable patch, mixed with a wildlife garden. Nuts, fruit, seeds, salad, green veg, shoots, twine, fungi… there’s an awful lot you can grow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above and encompassing all these things, a forest garden, like every garden, is a properly magical space just to be.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Green Tangle</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/the-green-tangle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jun 2018 13:07:48 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/the-green-tangle/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;All that doesn’t glitter isn’t not gold! Or, it’s okay to have a green garden like a #ForestGarden&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1746/42802735621_0af1bd28ab_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of a very green bed surrounded by grass path&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;The Green Tangle of Fruit Triangle at Forest Garden Wales&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;As the saying goes, “You can have a show garden &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; you can have a real garden”. Forest gardens definitely fall into the latter category, they’re first and foremost a productive and practical garden system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fruit Triangle at Forest Garden Wales (so called because it’s a triangle and there’s, er, lots of fruit) honestly is a bit of a green tangle. &lt;strong&gt;But&lt;/strong&gt; there is a beauty and diversity even in this relatively small space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post itself is a bit of a ramble, as I will unpick the green tangle plant by plant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do remember, &lt;strong&gt;flowers are allowed&lt;/strong&gt;, nay, &lt;em&gt;encouraged&lt;/em&gt;. Often edible and pollinator friendly, they also jolly the place up, and lest we forget &lt;a href=&#34;https://mobile.twitter.com/ForestGdnWales/status/1008341790204841984&#34;&gt;gardens are for people&lt;/a&gt;. The more you enjoy a space, the more you want to be in that space, the more you will care for that space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, first and in the foreground, I give you the glorious mallow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/900/28929400768_c090ebd3ef_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Photo of common Mallow in front of Japanese quince and with strawberry ground cover&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Malva sylvestris (common mallow)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a choice of many different species and varieties of mallow (have a look on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pfaf.org/&#34;&gt;PFAF&lt;/a&gt;), you can eat them raw and cooked, and they can thicken up sauces. And even &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; can grow them from seed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot going on the ground as well. One of my many mottos is “Mulch Everything”. We’ve used &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/unglamorous-grunt-work/&#34;&gt;bulk bought bark&lt;/a&gt; as a mulch but in the future, we’ll be using a &lt;a href=&#34;https://duckduckgo.com/?q=wood+chipper+domestic&amp;amp;t=ffab&amp;amp;iax=images&amp;amp;ia=images&#34;&gt;wood chipper&lt;/a&gt; on hedge cuttings and the willow coppice to create &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/does-woodchip-mulch-rob-nitrogen-from-the-soil/&#34;&gt;wood chip mulch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1723/42085868184_f4822aa422_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Small green leaves on mossy bark mulch&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Bark mulch with establishing Fragaria chiloensis (Chilean strawberry)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The living ground cover we’ve planted is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Fragaria+chiloensis&#34;&gt;Fragaria chiloensis&lt;/a&gt; (Chilean Strawberry), interspersed with some &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Glechoma+hederacea&#34;&gt;Glechomae hederacea&lt;/a&gt; (Alefoot).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1732/27934422947_bc04e1bc5b_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Strawberry leaves&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Fragaria chiloensis (Chilean strawberry) ground cover&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To allow the permanent ground cover a chance to get established, we’ve sown &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cotswoldseeds.com/product/mustard-sinapis-alba&#34;&gt;agriculturally sourced&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pfaf.org/user/plant.aspx?LatinName=Sinapis+alba&#34;&gt;Sinapis alba&lt;/a&gt; (White Mustard). This will die back after the summer, by which time the strawberries will be in full strawberry swing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/883/27934383627_d5877f38e9_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Yellow flowers and green foliage of the white mustard&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Alba sinapis (white mustard) temporary ground cover, in flower&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, onto the fruit. And what a lot of fruit there is. Everybody loves raspberries (apart from those of us who don’t). These are summer raspberries (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Rubus+idaeus&#34;&gt;Rubus idaeus&lt;/a&gt;) that have been rescued from a path restoration project, so no idea what variety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1729/42085781854_19233ab995_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;One ripe raspberry on a raspberry plant, with yellow flowers in the backgroudn&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;A rescued early Rubus idaeus (raspberry)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, the blackcurrants (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Ribes+nigrum&#34;&gt;Ribes nigrum&lt;/a&gt;) have been rescued from another part of the garden, I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; that they’re &amp;lsquo;Ben Nevis&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1721/42085503664_eda8038c32_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Top of blackcurrant, grass on left background, yellow flowered mustard on right&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Ribes nigrum &amp;lsquo;Ben Nevis&amp;rsquo; (blackcurrant)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And another garden rescuee is the gooseberry (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Ribes+uva-crispa&#34;&gt;Ribes uva-crispa&lt;/a&gt;)I found growing at right-angles from the hedge. I’m not overly concerned if it fruits or not, as it has a plucky survival story all of its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/883/28929735338_de52163403_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Barely visible wonky gooseberry in amongst green foliage&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;A rescued Ribes uva-crispa (gooseberry), a bit wonky from a few years growing in a hedge&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I realise that about 50% of our plants have been rescued, recycled or donated. Another one is the Japanese Raspberry (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pfaf.org/user/plant.aspx?latinname=Rubus+phoenicolasius&#34;&gt;Rubus phoenicolasius&lt;/a&gt;) from a neighbour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1784/42144298604_12b59d3d3b_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Jumble of wineberry leaves in amongst the green garden&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Rubus phoenicolasius (Japanese wineberry)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The semi-dwarf apple tree (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pfaf.org/user/plant.aspx?LatinName=Malus+domestica&#34;&gt;Malus domestica&lt;/a&gt;) has been rescued from where the summer house has been built, it’s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.orangepippin.com/apples/braeburn&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Braeburn&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt; on an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/rootstock-reference/&#34;&gt;M26&lt;/a&gt; rootsock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/899/42813717192_0e7e478684_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Small apple tree, comfrey in front, grass path and gate behind&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Malus domestica &amp;lsquo;Braeburn&amp;rsquo; (apple) on M26 rootstock&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last two items of fruit are the blueberry &amp;lsquo;Gold Traube&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Vaccinium+corymbosum&#34;&gt;Vaccinium corymbosum&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1749/28989373678_d691906560_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Blueberry&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Vaccinium corymbosum (Gold Traube)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the Japanese Qunice &amp;lsquo;Nivalis&amp;rsquo;, a scraggy plant if ever there was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/876/42813755632_1aee335f49_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Scraggy Japanese quince, lots of leaves&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Chaenomeles japonica &amp;lsquo;Nivalis&amp;rsquo; (Japanese quince)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To feed all this, we have plentiful outcrops of comfrey (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Symphytum+officinale&#34;&gt;Symphytum officinale &amp;lsquo;Bocking 14&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;), which are cut back a couple of times a year and laid directly under the fruit bushes to compost down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1750/42813664482_df19a88132_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Comfrey big pointy leaves&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Symphytum officinale &amp;lsquo;Bocking 14&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoyed the untangling of The Green Tangle. I do have plans for an Ornamental Maintenance-free Forest Garden, which will use the #ForestGarden palette for aesthetic effect. But that’s for another blog post 🙂.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How green is your garden?</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/how-green-is-your-garden/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2018 21:15:33 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/how-green-is-your-garden/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Gardening should be the most environmentally friendly of endeavours but that isn’t necessarily the case&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/944/28510026388_f9b1d2e52c_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of yellow mustard flowers in foreground with tree lined hedge and bark mulch in distance&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Forest Garden Wales, planting in progress&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;I came across a post about how to &lt;a href=&#34;https://modernmint.co.uk/capture-carbon/&#34;&gt;Capture carbon in your garden&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ModernMintLtd/&#34;&gt;@ModernMintLtd&lt;/a&gt;. Really simple, and not surprisingly, forest gardening ticks all the boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plant a tree&lt;br&gt;
✔️  &lt;em&gt;Part of the very definition of a forest garden!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve your soil (mulch, don’t dig)&lt;br&gt;
️✔️  &lt;em&gt;Use a living mulch, ie ground cover plants&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cover your soil with plants&lt;br&gt;
✔️️  &lt;em&gt;See above!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t use artificial fertiliser&lt;br&gt;
️✔️  &lt;em&gt;Use mineral accumulators &amp;amp; nitrogren fixers for nutrients&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use peat free compost&lt;br&gt;
️✔️  &lt;em&gt;Very little compost used, only peat-free potting compost for seedlings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were some ideas contributed by other people, and again, this is what we’re moving toward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;contributed-ideas&#34;&gt;Contributed ideas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No petrol based tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grow from seed at home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grow as much food as you can&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduce your lawn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t heat your greenhouse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are still using a petrol mower to keep the grass paths short on an acre field. Currently, it’s about 2 hours a week mowing but we’re constantly reducing the amount of grass that has to be cut. Also, it’s taking a while to shift our diet to home grown food, which is as much about knowledge of cooking and plants as it is about a desire to change. This is the third year of the forest garden, and it’s the first time we’ve really noticed an increase in the produce.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forest garden tours now public!</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/forest-garden-tours-now-public/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2018 12:06:39 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/forest-garden-tours-now-public/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Forest Garden Wales is now open for tours by individual members of the public. Tickets on Eventbrite 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/968/40947287805_348eb107c2_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Forest Garden tour poster&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Forest garden tours, first Saturday of the month, May–September inclusive!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;We’ve taken the plunge and opened up the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forestgarden.wales/tours/&#34;&gt;forest garden tours&lt;/a&gt; for individual members of the public to come along, rather than just taking group bookings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First Saturday of the month, May to September inclusive, here are those dates in full:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saturday 5th May&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saturday 2nd June&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saturday 7th July&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saturday 4th August&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saturday 1st September&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please book in advance, tickets from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/forest-garden-wales-tour-tickets-45399231323&#34;&gt;Eventbrite&lt;/a&gt;, £10 each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a bit risky, as in we’re not expecting vast numbers of people (the first Saturday is coming up already!) &lt;strong&gt;but&lt;/strong&gt; it is an opportunity to spread the word about forest gardening, and all the benefits. If you’re not sure what those benefits are, I will put them into buillet points for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Less maintenance&lt;/strong&gt;. No, really, &lt;strong&gt;less maintenance&lt;/strong&gt;. A forest garden isn’t a miracle cure but by the very design (perennials, ground cover, self-fertilising) they are &lt;strong&gt;less maintenance&lt;/strong&gt;. Doesn’t that sound attractive?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Less grass&lt;/strong&gt;. This is actually the same as above. But, there is generally less grass in a forest garden, just some paths. And less grass means… &lt;strong&gt;less mowing&lt;/strong&gt;. That’s right, even &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; maintenance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More wildlife&lt;/strong&gt;. Everybody likes wildlife. Wildlife likes wildlife, particularly for lunch. And forest gardens are, by nature, wildlife-friendly. There’s a great diversity of permanent cover and plant species, in different layers (trees, shrubs, ground cover). And diversity encourages wildlife.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stuff you can eat&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s like foraging in your own back garden, without having to ask the landowner’s permission (because you are the landowner).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stuff you can use&lt;/strong&gt;. Things like wood, poles, twine, dyes, herbals…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do come along if you’re in West Wales, and I’ll expound upon these bullet points for at least 3 hours. Whilst walking. Here’s a link to the tickets again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/forest-garden-wales-tour-tickets-45399231323&#34;&gt;forestgardenwales.eventbrite.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you 🙂&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My blue hay mulching experiment</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/my-bluegrass-mulching-experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2018 21:54:15 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/my-bluegrass-mulching-experiment/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Grass in Welsh is glaswellt, which translates as “blue hay”. I’m using freshly scythed grass as a mulch in the polytunnel 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/956/27854471018_c52428bf4d_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wooden hay rake leaning on apple tree in front of freshly scythed grass&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;It may look bucolic but I can tell you it’s hard work…&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;Last year I experimented with a green mulch in the polytunnel. It didn’t really work out, far too much growth and lots of time spent keeping the mulch down. Which kind of defeats the point of a mulch!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/908/40824169425_e46987dd4c_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Piles of freshly cut grass, young trees, polytunnel in background&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Mounds of grass ready for bagging up and distributing in polytunnel&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I’ve decided to stick with a grass/hay mulch, from the orchard area in the forest garden. I will cut down on the amount of grass but it is useful as a crop for mulching and as a habitat for wildlife (I think bumblebees nest in grass tussocks?), so I’ll keep an area of grass long-term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/978/26855161777_c8d7e8a642_z.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Polytunnel raised beds mulched with freshly cut grass&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The end setup, grass mulch on top to keep moisture in&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a series of soaker hoses under the surface, plastic funnels to water lower down, a layer of cow muck and then grass mulch on top to keep the moisture in. Tomatoes 🍅 to be planted out this afternoon!&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does woodchip mulch rob nitrogen from the soil?</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/does-woodchip-mulch-rob-nitrogen-from-the-soil/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 22:23:04 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/does-woodchip-mulch-rob-nitrogen-from-the-soil/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Many people believe that woodchip applied as a mulch around plants can tie-up nitrogen and cause deficiencies. Apparently not!&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/870/41116737764_16e3ee1953_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Woodchip used as a mulch in a border&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Woodchip mulch in a bed at Scolton Manor walled garden&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;I’m a big fan of Martin Crawford and all he has done to promote the understanding and practise of forest gardening. But as it is forest &lt;em&gt;gardening&lt;/em&gt;, there are obviously some opinions that are debatable, and woodchip as a mulch around living plants is one of them. He states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woodchip causes a nitrogen deficiency if used as a mulch around living plants&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;pp306, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.agroforestry.co.uk/product/creating-a-forest-garden-2/&#34;&gt;Creating a Forest Garden&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went to visit a chap called Stefan Cartwright who lives locally and who’s planting up a large site with coppice and a forest garden. He swears by woodchip mulch, and showed me some used on a willow coppicing area, with healthy plants and rich, worm-filled soil underneath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I did some research on that there internet, and I found &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sustainablelandscapesandgardens.com&#34;&gt;Linda Chalker-Scott&lt;/a&gt;’s excellent work on &lt;a href=&#34;https://puyallup.wsu.edu/lcs/&#34;&gt;busting horticultural myths&lt;/a&gt; over at Washington State University. I love a good evidence-based opinion. In an article entitled &lt;a href=&#34;https://puyallup.wsu.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/403/2015/03/wood-chips.pdf&#34;&gt;“Wood chip mulch: Landscape boon or bane?”&lt;/a&gt; in the 2007 issue of Master Gardener magazine, she states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concern:&lt;/strong&gt; Wood chip mulches will tie up nitrogen and cause deficiencies in plants.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Evidence:&lt;/strong&gt; Actually, many studies have demonstrated that woody mulch materials increase nutrient levels in soils and/or associated plant foliage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, it’s fine to use woodchip as a mulch around living plants, although she advises against using it in annual beds where the plants have very shallow and limited root systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This opens up a lot more possibilities, as I would imagine arborist wood chip is far more readily available than bark. Also, we have a &lt;strong&gt;lot&lt;/strong&gt; of woody material from hedges and general gardening, and it’s far more efficient (and cheaper!) to chip this on-site than to bring in material from outside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also means that I’ll have more mulching material available so that I can re-use the 1 metre plastic sheet mulch in the coppice and replace it with woodchip. Everyone’s a winner 🙂.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Now using Netlify CMS!</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/now-using-netlify-cms/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 12:55:44 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/now-using-netlify-cms/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;A bit of a geeky post about the software that powers forestgarden.wales&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/806/39708805630_e325983669_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Netlify CMS screen on forestgarden.wales&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Netlify CMS working on forestgarden.wales – note Blog and Status categories&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;With my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.growdigital.org/&#34;&gt;web designer/developer&lt;/a&gt; hat on, I built the Forest Garden Wales website using an amazing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.staticgen.com/&#34;&gt;static site generator&lt;/a&gt; called &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;, with my own socially-aware starter theme called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.indiego.org.uk/&#34;&gt;Indiego&lt;/a&gt;. Static site generators simply(sic) generate static pages without the complexity of a database. The plus points are speed, simplicity and price (for more advantages, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netlify.com/blog/2016/05/18/9-reasons-your-site-should-be-static/&#34;&gt;see this Netlify article&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The downside is that they can be daunting for a non-developer, with lots of editing text and terminals. The good folk at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netlify.com/&#34;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt; have made a lovely User Interface called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netlifycms.org/&#34;&gt;NetlifyCMS&lt;/a&gt; that eases the workflow for non-developer people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to see a similar User Interface for the installation process, so that setting up a new website is as easy as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wordpress.org/&#34;&gt;WordPress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to dig around the source code for forestgarden.wales, it’s available on GitHub: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/forestgardenwales/forestgarden.wales&#34;&gt;github.com/forestgardenwales/forestgarden.wales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big thank you to Netlify for such a cool tool 👍 😄&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heated propagator howto</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/heated-propagator-howto/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2018 16:43:09 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/heated-propagator-howto/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Instructions for making your own thermostatically controlled propagator, cribbed from @GWandShows&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/887/40495146015_44a35ccdcb_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Side view of thermostatic propagator with clear plastic lid in a shed&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Finished propagator, squeezed into a small shed!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/gardenersworld/video/toby_30minfix/heated_propagator.shtml&#34;&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/gardenersworld/video/toby_30minfix/heated_propagator.shtml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;equipment-needed&#34;&gt;Equipment needed:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Screwdriver&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13mm wood drill bit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knife&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pliers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6m long heating cable and compatible thermostatic control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Screws to hold the sides together and attach to base&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RCD device to plug into wall socket if your fuse board doesn&amp;rsquo;t already contain one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plastic bell cloches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 small bags sharp builders sand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;materials-needed&#34;&gt;Materials needed:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 x 60cm x 121cm flat marine&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6&amp;quot; x 1&amp;quot;, 8&#39; + &amp;lsquo;4 = 12&amp;rsquo;(3.6m) - 6&amp;quot; x 1&amp;quot;, 8&#39; + &amp;lsquo;4 = 12&amp;rsquo;(3.6m)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 x 15cm wide, 2.5cm thick, 60 cm long edging boards&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Old plastic sacks to line the base&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharp sand to fill box to a depth of 10cm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ply, 2&amp;rsquo;x4&#39;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6&amp;quot; x 1&amp;quot;, 12&#39;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-to-do&#34;&gt;What to do:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You must be competent and confident at wiring / rewiring a plug to attempt this. If in doubt contact a qualified electrician.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When working with the cable and thermostat, please follow the instructions supplied by the manufacturer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A 6m heating cable is required for an 8sq ft heated bed; other lengths are available so check with the manufacturer which one is required for the size of propagator you are making.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start by fixing the edging boards together by screwing into the ends and into the base all the way round. Line the box with old compost bags or polythene to help keep the moisture away from the wood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evenly spread a 2in layer of damp sharp sand over the base.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lay the heating cable out on the sand, firming it in slightly to keep it in place, using the pattern suggested in the instruction sheet supplied with it. Add another 2in of damp sand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drill a hole in the side of the propagator base which is big enough to feed the correct end of the heating cable through (read the instructions if in doubt which end to use); feed the cable through carefully.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mount the thermostat on the side of the box at the correct height for the temperature probe to sit towards the top of the sand layer and not in contact with the heating cable. Before screwing the box in position you will need to make a hole, slightly larger in diameter than the probe, in the side of the box to feed the temperature probing rod through; it is easiest to do this before the thermostat is wired up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Following the instructions carefully, and with the unit unplugged, wire the colour coded wires from the heating cable into the correct terminals of the thermostat unit (if in doubt consult a qualified electrician for this bit). Tighten securely and also tighten up the cable securing screw where the cable was fed into the unit. Finally screw the wire thermostat box onto the side of the box. Plug it into a RCD (residual current device) protected socket. Switch on and set to 21°C. Check that the pilot light is on and that the thermostat switches on and off as the temperature dial is turned up and down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use plastic bell cloches to maintain the moisture over any pots of cuttings which are placed on the heated sand bed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;suppliers&#34;&gt;Suppliers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parasene Soil Warming Cable - 6m Length 75 Watts Product Code : 210/6M, Barcode - 5013554142879  £17.99
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.garden4less.co.uk/parasene-soil-warming-cable.asp&#34;&gt;http://www.garden4less.co.uk/parasene-soil-warming-cable.asp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parasene thermostat £28.99&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.garden4less.co.uk/proddetail.asp?prod=200&#34;&gt;http://www.garden4less.co.uk/proddetail.asp?prod=200&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forest garden tours now operating!</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/tours-now-operating/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 13:16:46 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/tours-now-operating/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Thanks to inspriation from The People’s Orchard and Permaculture Tywi, we now offer a half-day forest garden tour and talk! £10 per person, minimum 5 people&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/813/40249165324_5628e9a1e9_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of polytunnel on a slope with raised beds to the side, mature leafless trees behind and blue sky&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;The polytunnel, raised beds and propagation area in the forest garden&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;After the incredibly positive and encouraging feedback from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stdogmaelsabbey.org.uk/peoplesorchard&#34;&gt;The People’s Orchard&lt;/a&gt; and Permaculture Tywi, we’ve decided to offer a half-day tour and talk of our forest garden in Ceredigion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concerns that the garden isn’t established enough proved to be misfounded: the feedback we had was that a newly-established forest garden is in many ways an advantage for those wanting to find out about forest gardening. People can &lt;strong&gt;see&lt;/strong&gt; the structure and planting of the land far more clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we plan is to create the Ornamental Maintenance-free Forest Garden (OMG!), there will be plenty of barebones structure for visitors to learn from for quite a while yet!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more details, visit the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forestgarden.wales/tours/&#34;&gt;forest garden tour page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Order of Things</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/the-order-of-things/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 10:02:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/the-order-of-things/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;“Critical” was my word of the day on a recent tour, so I thought I’d formalise the list of things I think are critical when creating a forest garden&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4773/27120257158_84e4c27cee_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Small raised bed with bark mulch and small plants, old wheelbarrow behind&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Replanted Rubus nepalensis ground cover propagation bed. Start early!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Windbreaks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Propagation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Canopy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mulch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ground cover&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rabbit fence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, this probably applies equally to &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; gardens!&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The People’s Orchard visit Forest Garden Wales</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/the-peoples-orchard-visit-forest-garden-wales/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Apr 2018 09:51:47 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/the-peoples-orchard-visit-forest-garden-wales/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;A legion of People Orchardoers made the inaugural tour around Forest Garden Wales&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/892/39482524460_b525c9bd31_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Five peoople about to plant trees, in front of a ruined building&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;I forgot to take photos, so here’s one of The People’s Orchard back in St Dogmaels&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;After giving my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forestgarden.wales/talks/intro/#1&#34;&gt;first ever forest garden talk&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/peoplesorchardstdogs/&#34;&gt;The People’s Orchard&lt;/a&gt; back in March, Nia asked if they could have tour of Forest Garden Wales own forest garden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t thought that people would be interested in a &lt;em&gt;developing&lt;/em&gt; forest garden. We started planting canopy trees and windbreaks two years ago, and are about halfway through planting the ground cover and shrub layer. This time of year, all the trees look like sticks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, the People said Yes, that it was actually good to be able to see the planning and early stages of the garden. The feedback was so positive, we’ve decided to run forest garden tours this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought maybe half a dozen Orchardoers would arrive on what started out as a promisingly sunny day and degenerated into all-too-familiar windy &amp;amp; cold combo day. In the event &lt;strong&gt;15&lt;/strong&gt; Orchardoers arrived! That’s quite a lot of people, and they managed to polish off a fair amount of &lt;a href=&#34;http://simp.ly/publish/L624C8&#34;&gt;Vegan Chocolate Brownie&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was so good to have friendly, positive and engaging folk as the first ever visitors, as it helped shape ideas how to best deliver a forest garden tour, how to keep people’s interest and how to relate what you’ve learned to what they need. Hint: a map, chocolate brownies and a warm room help!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big smiley thank you to everyone who came along! 😃&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The promise of planting a tree</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/the-promise-of-planting-a-tree/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2018 19:36:54 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/the-promise-of-planting-a-tree/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Fun but serious work on Thursday morning, planting an apple and plum orchard by the car park at Poppit Sands, St Dogmaels, Pembrokeshire&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/881/27226348918_1ba89c9b57_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;People planting trees on bracken covered mound, field &amp; hill in background&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Nia and volunteers planting trees on Martin’s mound, ’twixt the hills &amp; the sea&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;There is nothing like the promise of planting a tree. On an overcast Thursday morning in mid-winter late April, Nia and Sophie from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stdogmaelsabbey.org.uk/peoplesorchard&#34;&gt;The People’s Orchard&lt;/a&gt;, with experienced orchardist Martin Hayes, led a small band of resilient volunteers in planting apple and plum trees by the car park at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.visitpembrokeshire.com/explore-pembrokeshire/beaches/poppit-sands/&#34;&gt;Poppit Sands&lt;/a&gt; in Pembrokeshire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holiday makers decant in the car park and scramble to the sea, casting nary a glance toward the area overgrown with bracken, dog rose and bramble, and it bears an air of mild neglect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A grass path circles the main part, with a mound in the middle, and Martin decided to plant the larger apple trees, all Welsh varieties, on the outside. On the inside, smaller apple trees were planted. The plums, on a rather vigorous rootstock, were given some more space on the other side of the path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/880/40389452674_37533542fc_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Newly planted apple trees with rabbit guards, car park and sand dunes in the distance&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;View alongside of newly planted apple area, toward the car park&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a fantastic story behind the small apple trees: on a previous visit, Martin discovered half a dozen or so hybridized apple trees on the site of the old picnic area from the 1960s, trees that had grown from the discarded apple cores of picnicking holiday makers. He had the more promising trees (one of them with a bubblegum aroma!) grafted to provide stock for the rejuventated area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/890/41099469581_c165a831fb_z_d.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Man holding twigs standing in dunes, secateurs in hand&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Martin Hayes with cuttings from the bubblegum tree, where the old picnic site used to be&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the planting, it felt as if everyone could feel the promise of the trees. How, in a few short years, children on a jolly to the beach would take a diversion to the orchard and pick apples to eat. Despite the grey skies, everything was lifted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Promises also go both ways. The biggest lesson I’ve learnt on the People’s Orchard’s workshops is that &lt;strong&gt;cultivated fruit trees need looking after&lt;/strong&gt;. It is a commitment, a promise. The trees at Poppit Sands will need the bracken cutting back, guards putting up to protect from lawnmowers and pruning every year. And in return, fruit for future generations.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What blogging software do you use?</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/what-blogging-software-do-you-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Mar 2018 10:46:19 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/what-blogging-software-do-you-use/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;After days of building my own blog, I’m curious as to what other people are using and how well it fits in with social media.&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/819/40359939864_77cd398e1a_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Forest Garden Wales website in browser, with browser tools showing&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;The new Forest Garden Wales website. Was it worth it?!?&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;My alter ego is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/jake-rayson-designer/&#34;&gt;a web designer&lt;/a&gt;. This is a blessing and a curse, for I have spent &lt;strong&gt;too long&lt;/strong&gt; building the new &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forestgarden.wales&#34;&gt;Forest Garden Wales website blog&lt;/a&gt; and not enought time gardening. I ended up using &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;, a rather nifty &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.staticgen.com/&#34;&gt;static site generator&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netlify.com/blog/2016/05/18/9-reasons-your-site-should-be-static/&#34;&gt;geekyish alternative&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://wordpress.org/&#34;&gt;WordPress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would I have been better off using off-the-shelf blogging software? I really don’t know, which is why I’m keen to find out what other people are using – &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.blogger.com/&#34;&gt;Blogger&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tumblr.com/&#34;&gt;Tumblr&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.weebly.com/uk&#34;&gt;Weebly&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;WordPress.com&lt;/a&gt;, self-hosted WordPress? And are people able to promote their posts on different social media? I know you can use &lt;a href=&#34;https://wordpress.org/plugins/jetpack/&#34;&gt;JetPack&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://wordpress.org/plugins/social-networks-auto-poster-facebook-twitter-g/&#34;&gt;SNAP&lt;/a&gt; for WordPress but I’ve no real idea about other platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main reason for building my own blog is because I want to &lt;strong&gt;speed up&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;secure&lt;/strong&gt; my garden blogging and social media workflow whilst retaining control over my content (oh, and because I can 😜). Hopefully, this very blog post will be automatically published to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ForestGdnWales&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/Forest-Garden-Wales&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/111290684473488016210&#34;&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;forestgardenwales.wordpress.com&#34;&gt;WordPress&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/company/forest-garden-wales/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;. At the same time, the content will &lt;strong&gt;always&lt;/strong&gt; be available on this site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this control of your own work is a big issue, particularly in the light of recent Facebook revelations about their business model (which applies equally to Google et al). Combined with &lt;a href=&#34;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/ublock-origin/&#34;&gt;tracker&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/ublock-origin/cjpalhdlnbpafiamejdnhcphjbkeiagm?hl=en&#34;&gt;blockers&lt;/a&gt;, it’s time to take your privacy back!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s still an awful lot left to do this website (self-hosted photos rather than using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/&#34;&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netlifycms.org/&#34;&gt;nice User Interface&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://staticman.net/&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://indieweb.org/webmention&#34;&gt;webmentions&lt;/a&gt; etc.)
but hopefully I can share some of the lessons I’ve learned with other garden bloggers 😄.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes from Wild Bees in Pembrokeshire talk</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/bee-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/bee-notes/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Wild Bees in Pembrokeshire - an introduction to Species, Diversity and Learning to Record Wildlife with Clare Flynn @wildaboutnature, talk at Moylegrove Old School Hall, Tue 23 Jan 7.30pm&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4665/28421254799_a8edf95f46_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Backs of heads looking at projector screen in hall&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Wild Bees in Pembrokeshire talk with Clare Flynn at Moylegrove Old School Hall, Tue 23 Jan 7.30pm, photo via @wildaboutnature&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;Clare Flynn, County Recorder, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/wildaboutnature&#34;&gt;@wildaboutnature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reasons-for-biological-recording&#34;&gt;Reasons for Biological Recording&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reliable biological data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conservation - knowing what is there&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monitoring populations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Planning land use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provides data for academic research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 paths:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;County recorders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Local Records Centres LERC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;National recording schemes eg MCS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;West Wales Biodiversity Information Centre, WWBIC, Whitland&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;National Plant Monitoring Scheme&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bees, Wasps &amp;amp; Ants Recording Centre&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;biological-record&#34;&gt;Biological record&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who: recorder - full details&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What: species - backup ID with photo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where: location - 6 figure grid reference&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When: date - time stamp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;our farmland is not biodiverse at all&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are there specific plants that help with biodiversity? Trees. Species?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Question: what are the most beneficial species for biodiversity? Do they have to be native?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bees&#34;&gt;Bees&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did a four day course on bumblebees and I was hooked&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;World:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;25,000 species solitary bee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;250 species bumblebee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7 species honey bee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UK:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;243 species solitary bee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;25 species bumblebee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 species honey bee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Willow and dandelions for early bees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo via &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/wildaboutnature/&#34;&gt;@wildaboutnature&lt;/a&gt; tweet:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://mobile.twitter.com/wildaboutnature/status/956127645003124736&#34;&gt;https://mobile.twitter.com/wildaboutnature/status/956127645003124736&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joy of Plants app for iPhone</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/joy-of-plants/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/joy-of-plants/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;A quick heads up for handy plants database app&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4750/39354215564_ed6ff6b9c6_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshots of Joy of Plants database app&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Joy of Plants app, alas only avaiable on iPhone&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;On a visit to &lt;a href=&#34;http://penralltnursery.co.uk&#34;&gt;Penrallt Garden Centre&lt;/a&gt; last year, I was trying to track down &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=mentha+longifolia&#34;&gt;Mentha longifolia&lt;/a&gt; (horse mint) after seeing it used as a rampant ground cover on Martin Crawford’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.agroforestry.co.uk/product/forest-gardening-food-forests-design-course/&#34;&gt;forest gardening course&lt;/a&gt;. The staff member pulled out her iPhone and looked it up for me, on a very handy app called &lt;a href=&#34;https://joyofplants.com/iphone.php&#34;&gt;Joy of Plants&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I installed it on my phone, and now use it most weeks; it’s really good for detailed information and photographs of specific varieties, and covers a lot of forest garden favourites as well. In combination with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/Default.aspx&#34;&gt;Plants for a Future&lt;/a&gt;, a superb resource for forest gardening, all my plant database needs are pretty much met 🙂&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I do find strange though is that, despite the vast and detailed amount of work that has obviously gone in to &lt;a href=&#34;https://joyofplants.com/&#34;&gt;Joy of Plants&lt;/a&gt;, it’s not that widely publicised in the ”gardening social circles” which I’ve started researching. My guess is that the work is one thing, the networking another – all the more reason to join in with groups like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/groups/gdnbloggers/&#34;&gt;Garden Bloggers #gdnbloggers&lt;/a&gt; to help spread the word of good work.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My maiden forest garden talk!</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/forest-garden-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/forest-garden-talk/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;A 1 hour talk entitled ‘An introduction to forest gardening’, St Dogmaels Abbey, 7.30PM Friday 23rd February 2018, hosted by The People’s Orchard&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4741/25739902778_6d97694689_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Grass path leading to mature trees, young hedge on the right, sheet mulch on the left&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Our young forest garden in the making&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;The good people at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/peoplesorchardstdogs/&#34;&gt;The People’s Orchard&lt;/a&gt; are very kindly hosting my very first public talk about forest gardening. It’ll be held at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stdogmaelsabbey.org.uk/contact.php&#34;&gt;St Dogmaels Abbey&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://binged.it/2DW5Hb0&#34;&gt;SA43 3DX&lt;/a&gt; in Pembrokeshire, near Cardigan, West Wales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s an introduction to forest gardening, just an hour, so it will be about the principles and our practical experience and gotchas about starting out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will be putting the slides online, once I’ve worked out a decent way of storing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More details to follow!&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plants that make mycorrhizal associations</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/list-mycorrhizal-associations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/list-mycorrhizal-associations/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Excerpt from Radical Mycology listing which plants have which mycorrhizal associations&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4705/28246251219_26717dcbbf_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Radical Mycology - decompose toxins to cultivate life&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Banner image from Radical Mycology website&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;Edited notes from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://radicalmycology.com/&#34;&gt;Radical Mycology&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chthaeus.com/Radical-Mycology-by-Peter-McCoy-p/b-rmp.htm&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://radicalmycology.com/peters-bio/&#34;&gt;Peter McCoy&lt;/a&gt;. Handy knowledge when &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/how-to-make-your-own-mycorrhizal-fungi/&#34;&gt;making your own mycorrhizal inoculant&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#arbuscular-endo-mycorrhizal-plants-80-90-&#34;&gt;Arbuscular (endo)mycorrhizal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;non-mycorrhizal-plants-5-&#34;&gt;Non-mycorrhizal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;ectomycorrhizal-ecm-plants-5-&#34;&gt;Ectomycorrhizal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-arbuscular-endomycorrhizal-plants-80-90&#34;&gt;1. Arbuscular (Endo)mycorrhizal plants (80-90%)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority of wild plants, including shrubs, wildflowers and broad leaf trees associate with AM, as do redwood, cedar and juniper trees. These include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Almost all groups of Pteridophyta&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most groups of Gymnospermae&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Majority of families in the Angiospermae&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All palms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All plants in the Bryophyta&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Almost all bulb plants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anything related to roses, apples, peaches, pears, strawberries etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most tropical plants (apart from orchids)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Majority of horticultural species&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Almost all crop plants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All &lt;em&gt;cultivated&lt;/em&gt; grasses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shrubs and foliage plants except for Rhododendron, Azalea and Heath&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Berries except for blueberries, cranberries and lingonberries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nut trees except pecan, hazelnuts and filberts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fruit trees including tropical fruits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many wetland/aquatic species except rushes and horsetails&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-non-mycorrhizal-plants-5&#34;&gt;2. Non-mycorrhizal plants (5%)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;brassicaceae&#34;&gt;Brassicaceae&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Broccoli&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brussels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cabbage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cauliflower&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rutabaga&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;others&#34;&gt;Others&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carnation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mustard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orchids&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rush&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sedge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spinach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-ectomycorrhizal-ecm-plants-5&#34;&gt;3. Ectomycorrhizal (ECM) plants (5%)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Primary plant families:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pinaceae&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fagaceae&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Betulaceae&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salicaceae&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dipterocarpaceae&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some species in the Cupressaceae and most species in the Myrtaceae and Caesalpinoideae also form ECM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some plant groups that benefit from ectomycorrhizal fungi include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alder (endo/ecto)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arborvitae&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arctostaphylos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aspen (endo/ecto)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basswood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beech&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Birch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chestnut&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chinquapin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cottonwood (endo/ecto)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Douglas-Fir&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eucalyptus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Filbert&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fir&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hazelnut&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hickory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hemlock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Larch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linden&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Madrone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manzanita&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oak&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pecan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Poplar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spruce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Willow (endo/ecto)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to make your own mycorrhizal fungi</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/make-your-own-mychorrizal-inoculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/make-your-own-mychorrizal-inoculum/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;You can make your own arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi inoculant, like rootgrow™, for adding to roots for healthier plants&lt;/p&gt;
        
        &lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many gardeners add mycorrhizal fungi (like &lt;a href=&#34;http://chaosfungorum.co.uk/?post_type=product&#34;&gt;Chaos Fungorum&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rootgrow.co.uk/mycorrhizal-fungi.html&#34;&gt;rootgrow™&lt;/a&gt;) to roots when planting. The good people at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/hyphaeshroomery/&#34;&gt;Hyphae Shroomery&lt;/a&gt; very kindly sent instructions from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sunseed.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/A-SIMPLE-METHOD-FOR-MAKING-YOUR-OWN-MYCORRHIZAL-INOCULUM.pdf&#34;&gt;Sunseed Desert Technology&lt;/a&gt; on how to make your mycorrhizal fungi inoculant. These are my abbreviated notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will take 3 months to grow the inoculant, and you will need one large 30 litre pot or several smaller ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, it will be &lt;strong&gt;arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF)&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AMF form symbioses with 80% of plant species, including the majority of herbaceous and annual species, most arid and semi-arid woody species and tropical hardwoods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The other main type is the Ectomycorrhizal fungi: these colonize the roots of most temperate and boreal tree species – conifers, oaks, beech etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few plant families do not form mycorrhizas, notably the cabbage and beet families. (The main non-mycorrhizal plant families are: Brassicaceae, Amaranthaceae, Caryophyllaceae and Chenopodiaceae (normally)).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-collect-starter-soil&#34;&gt;1. Collect starter soil&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In temperate regions, hedgerows, thickets and thriving perennial grasslands that have not been cultivated recently are good sources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you plan to use the inoculum with tree seedlings, there can be special benefit in collecting some of the starter soil from under healthy trees of the same species.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Method:&lt;/strong&gt; Clear away about half square metre of the vegetation underneath your target plant. Dig down to a depth of about 25cm collecting the soil and as many fine roots as possible. It is better, but not essential, to collect from under several different trees and shrubs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With stony soil, sieve it to get rid of large stones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-multiply-mycorrhiza&#34;&gt;2. Multiply mycorrhiza&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Position pots where they can be inspected, watered and left alone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill 30 litre pot or several 5 litre pots with starter soil.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose combination of grassy species (eg maize, millet, sorghum, oats, wheat) or an allium (onion, leek), with a species of legume (beans, peas, lentils, alfalfa, clover).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These “bait plants” will become infected with the mycorrhizal fungus causing the fungal population to multiply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sow seeds closer than normal, alternating the species.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep regularly watered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-harvest&#34;&gt;3. Harvest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ten days before using inoculant, cut down bait plants at base of the stem and stop watering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This kills the plant and tricks fungus into producing spores.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After the ten days, pull up roots, chop into 1cm pieces, mix back into soil.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-using-inoculant&#34;&gt;4. Using inoculant&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trees from seed:&lt;/strong&gt; add inoculant layer ⅓ way down in pot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pre-grown trees:&lt;/strong&gt; add spade-full of inoculant to bottom of hole&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crops:&lt;/strong&gt; pinch of inoculant into any hole, or sprinkle in bottom of drill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don’t stake fruit trees</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/dont-stake-fruit-trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/dont-stake-fruit-trees/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;I am always wary of outright statements but this one is interesting and time saving&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4587/38517307965_1f502a7949_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of hand holding tree branch buds&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Apple tree buds&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;On a recent Planting &amp;amp; Pruning workshop held by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stdogmaelsabbey.org.uk/peoplesorchard&#34;&gt;The People’s Orchard&lt;/a&gt;, the orchardist Martin Hayes said a very interesting thing: &lt;strong&gt;don’t stake fruit trees unless they are dwarf&lt;/strong&gt; ie if they are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/rootstock-reference/&#34;&gt;M26 or smaller&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, this encourages far healthier and more robust root growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had read differently, so apart from very small trees, ours are all staked at the bottom of the trunk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is something that strikes me about gardening in general, that there are just so many opinions, and so many of them conflicting. But I’m going with Martin’s advice, as he knows his onions.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About the name…</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/about-the-name/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/about-the-name/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;A small clarification about the origins of the name Forest Garden Wales&lt;/p&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;The name means “a forest garden, in Wales”. It does &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; mean “The Only Forest Garden in Wales”. There are lots of other Welsh forest gardens, all of them lovely 🙂.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Welsh for forest garden is &lt;strong&gt;gardd fforest&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forest Garden Design Course notes 2016</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/course-notes-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/course-notes-2016/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Notes from Martin Crawford forest garden course back in the summer of 2016&lt;/p&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;Traditional agricultural science can’t cope with complexity of forest garden, 100+ species of plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science &amp;amp; complex systems (thinking of chaos theory)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;energy-efficiency&#34;&gt;Energy efficiency&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forest Garden 1:40 Arable 1: 4 Animal 1: 0.8&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yield &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; input&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ideas&#34;&gt;Ideas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Berberis as windbreak, useful for easterly protection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bowles Hybrid willow, 1.2m wide, non-competitive roots, vestigiate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People space where paths converge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Batboxes in trees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;coppice&#34;&gt;Coppice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sweet chestnuts coppice crop 6 years for fence posts - last 10-15 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hazels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Redwoods for fenceposts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you forecast the future, you will be doomed to fail&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;## Spacing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tree spacing ¼ – ½ of combined tree diameters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But, can plant small trees under high trees eg Italian alder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Windbreak protection is 3 * the height, eg 2m hedge gives 6m protection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cross pollinators 2-3 trees apart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nitrogen fixing trees can be 30–40m away&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ash roots as wide as high (same for poplar). Normally 1/3 of height.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many small errors multiply and lead to great unhappiness&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;out-in-the-garden&#34;&gt;Out in the garden&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Toona sinensis - pollard every winter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tilia cordata - pollard every 3-4 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;White mulberry - leaf crop cooked, high in protein&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cornus kousa - 25m in 20 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Valerian - potassium accelerator cut for onsite mulch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plum yew - ripe in November&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phyllostachys
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shade tolerant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can grow 25cm per day!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can spread 2-3m per year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maintenance 1-2 times per year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5m high, 2cm canes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;80 canes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;120 shoots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10 shoots per meal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pear, medlar, hawthorn can graft on existing hawthorn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crataegus ellwegariana - tarpaulin on ground, shake branches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Black locust for timber 20-30 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;## Most attractive fruit colours to birds&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In descending order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Purple&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Red&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orange&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Black (mulberries)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cornus capitata - edible fruit 3.5-4cm end Nov, banana flavour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zanthoxylum schinifolium - leaves for flavouring in spring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pineapple guava&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sweet chestnut Marigoule, early ripening 30-35kg. Harvest with tarpaulin, frequently especially if windy. Knock the branches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syrian hawthorn, thornless, delicious raw&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;European bladdernut - shade tolerant, understorey, pistachio flavour nuts, 1cm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bog myrtle - N-fixer, armoatic leaves, insect repellent, lovely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tibetan whitebeam - fruits 2cm like marzipan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bamboo for playground&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shrubby alders for extra N, lie prunings flat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zanthoxylum alatum Nepalese pepper, fragrance like black pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compost toilet in tent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Swamp cypress, v. tolerant of damp, hard wood, coppice for fence posts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;## Outside again, Saturday afternoon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self-seeding only happens in context&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ground ivy (Glechoma hederacea), aromatic, good cover, good bee plant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japanese &amp;amp; Chinese yam, hardy in UK, raosted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turkish rocket, cooked. Evergreen in UK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ostrich fern - for shrubbery late March&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lemon balm, mint, oregano, possibly anti-bacterial, anti-fungal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japanese butterbur (Petasites japonicus)- damp shade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solomons Seal, Polyganatum biflorum - damp shade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let raspberries move&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turkish rhubarb (Rheum palmatum) - fairly shade tolerant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gunnera - N-fixing, in leaf stalks by algae&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sweet cicely - perennial: leaf, seed and root crop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hops for shoots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nepalese raspberry - shade, fanatastic ground cover for woodland&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maintenance: 1 day per week for 2 acre garden over the year. Efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most perennials 1-5 months germination!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Purslane - bettroot flavoured, shde, self-seeding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pulmonaria - bee plant &amp;amp; accumulator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[img]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hop
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grow up lower branches of Italian alder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 plant provides 100g dried hops, enough for 50 litres beer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3-4 shoots going up, Apr-Jul/Aug - for the rest, harvest the hop shoots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meadowseet - lovely feathery cream flowers, 2m, bee plant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Babbingtons leek
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;harvest as leek, cut shot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;distribute bulbils by broadcast in light groundcover&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;garlicky flavour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Korean raspberry good for shade under treas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ground-cover-techniques&#34;&gt;Ground cover techniques&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mulch strip, moving plants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3-10 plants per m²&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set up mother beds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dwarf comfrey, good spreading cover. Don&amp;rsquo;t cut for mulch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Periwinkle - flowers all year, good evergreen cover for shade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Swiss mint - type of mint for teas, not particularly spreading&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tropaeolum tuberosum (Mashua) perennial nasturtium
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tuber very productive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;leave in the ground, just harvest what you need, leave tubers to regrow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;## SUNDAY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prof. Martin Wolfe, Organic Research Centre&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrated Forest Gardening - worth a read&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eric Toensmeier &amp;lsquo;Edible Forest Gardens&amp;rsquo; 2 vols, quite academic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;### FGN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aim to facilitate visits to other members gardens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About 200, 160 in UK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;nutrient-budgets&#34;&gt;Nutrient budgets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heavy cropping fruits require extra N, 6-10 g/m² per year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rough rule - 2/3 area of heavy cropping plant to be N-fixing plants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portable compost toilet
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dig hole&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use for one season&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill and move&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If pH les than 6.0, then lime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-the-new-forest-garden&#34;&gt;In the new forest garden&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Forest Garden Greenhouse by Jerome Osentowski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transitional ground cover - trefoil, clover, mustard etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;transitional-ground-cover-process&#34;&gt;Transitional ground cover process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put down chipped bark&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plant perennials and long term cover (eg strawberries)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plant temporary cover thickly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strawberry expands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plant comfrey around fruit trees!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All mallows have edible leaves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Train bramble fruits (thornless) on to Elaeagnus umbellata&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liquorice, horseradish - eat young leaves in spring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;400m² (1 acre) enough for family of four&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;### Sea buckthorn harvesting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut whole fruting branch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freezer for 1 hour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tap &amp;amp; fruits come off&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harvest from sides, not upward growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;propogation&#34;&gt;Propogation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seaweed solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 days nettle &amp;amp; comfrey feed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mulch 6 months for grass, 12 morths for docks &amp;amp; dandelions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;predator-strips&#34;&gt;Predator strips&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Senecio (Brachyglottis)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meadowsweet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sweet cicely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For land-based work, you have to be efficient&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;harvesting-nuts--apples&#34;&gt;Harvesting nuts &amp;amp; apples&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tap the branches with big stick if it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been windy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harvest nuts frequently, every 2 days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each tree has approx 2 week harvest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nut Wizard £60 - can use with chestnuts once free from burr&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chestnut harvest end September&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure ground cover under nut tree is short or mown eg wild garlic dies back or cut comfrey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Silky 3.6m telescopic pruning saw&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nut drying machine 35°C - 1kW heater with fan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;preparing-chestnuts&#34;&gt;Preparing chestnuts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chestnuts 60% water (cf walnuts), need 50-55°C in shell to dry, 3 days. Shells crack easier when dry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put chestnuts in hessian sack, bash on concrete, skin comes off&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To use dried chestnuts, soak overnight in water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cook 40 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hawos electric stone mill, designed for grain, will smash nuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mushrooms&#34;&gt;Mushrooms&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oyster&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shitake - easiest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fresh logs, no less than 2 months old&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Denser wood preferred
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oak - 10-12 years mushrooms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alder - 6 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anne Miller, Scotland, for fungus spawn &amp;amp; food grade wax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High protein crop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Store logs somwhere shady and damp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chaos funorum for edible fungus inoculant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paul Stamets - ideas and books&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;shocking-the-shitake-log&#34;&gt;Shocking the Shitake log&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Soak the log overnight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bang &lt;strong&gt;hard&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep out of way of slugs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buds appear after week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rest for 3 months&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shock every 3 months&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harvest shitake 7-8cm, quickly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 kilo every 3 months, 30 kilos over 10 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;propogating-mycelium&#34;&gt;Propogating mycelium&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put inoculated log into thick plastic sack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep for one year, winter to winter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scrape off mycelium, put into holes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cleft-grafting&#34;&gt;Cleft grafting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sloe - graft plums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hawthorn - graft medlar, pear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buy graft wood from Brogdale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut graftwood in January on dry, sunny day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put in fridge for up to 3 months&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In spring, graft in April/May&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cleft graft easiest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Straight split, no side branches. Lever with screwdriver&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graftwood 1cm-70mm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leave 2-3 buds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Line up &lt;em&gt;inner&lt;/em&gt; edge of dark bark&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wax over surface using grafting wax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will grow to full width&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As existing tree, will grow vigorously&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Italian grafting pliers available (Brondesbury Garden Centre)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;apple-grafting&#34;&gt;Apple grafting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plant apple rootstock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let grow for 2-3 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut 2cm branch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graft wood on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;kiwi&#34;&gt;Kiwi&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Climbing kiwi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coppice with tree every 3-4 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grow on South side&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The People’s Orchard pruning and planting workshop</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/the-peoples-orchard-pruning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/the-peoples-orchard-pruning/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Notes from another excellent pruning and planting workshop with Martin Hayes, Orchardist, near Llandudoch in Pembrokeshire&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4770/39784408711_e356f0e0fb_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Man pruning goblet shape fruit tree with onlooker&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Martin Hayes, Orchardist, pruning goblet shape fruit tree&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stdogmaelsabbey.org.uk/peoplesorchard&#34;&gt;The People’s Orchard&lt;/a&gt; put on another pruning and planting workshop today, over at Waun Segur farm in Llandudoch. There was an orchard planted with large &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/rootstock-reference/&#34;&gt;M25 rootstock&lt;/a&gt; apple trees. The large, cat-like group of volunteers planted some more, including the exotic and possibly unique (pending genetic testing) Poppit Sands apple, found growing wild in the tough conditions of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.visitpembrokeshire.com/explore-pembrokeshire/beaches/poppit-sands/&#34;&gt;Poppit Sands&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I managed to cobble together some notes, which really are for my own benefit but if you can glean any sense or usefulness, all the better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t stake fruit trees unless they are dwarf, ie M26 and smaller (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/rootstock-reference/&#34;&gt;rootstock reference&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the smallest hole possible for the root ball when planting. Don’t break up the soil, you want to leave it firm so that the roots can grip and take hold.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There were M25 trees there which &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; been staked, and you could see by rocking them how stunted their root growth was.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standard tree just means a tree that has it’s lower branches raised so that cows can’t eat them (which means they have to be M25 size otherwise there’d be no fruit!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Half standard tree is one with lower branches raised so that sheep can’t eat them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martin’s preferred tree sheep is a Christmas Tree Shape for MM106 size and smaller (let large trees do their own thing). The only reference I could quickly find in a cursory search is a PDF called &lt;a href=&#34;http://growables.org/information/documents/trainingpruning.pdf&#34;&gt;Training and Pruning Fruit Trees&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncsu.edu/&#34;&gt;North Carolina State University&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three year cycle when planting a tree:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sleep - tree puts on root growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creep - upper growth slow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leap - things start speeding up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prune all inward pointing branches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prune to branch or bud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every new cut suppresses sap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For Christmas Tree shape, need to select central leader. Need to make it tallest by cutting back height of competing branches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dog leg pruning suppresses upward growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Straight leader encourages upward growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prune fruit trees every year after year 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you transplant a tree, cut branches to a ⅓ (check this!!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blank canvas and the Prickly Quad</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/blank-canvas-and-the-prickly-quad/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/blank-canvas-and-the-prickly-quad/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;The sheet mulch is up, the soil is bare and my mind is blank&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4612/39763874211_2ab689e125_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of bare earth prepared bed, trees to the back, grass path to the front&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Bare earth, blank mind&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;The idea of a blank canvas fills me with an odd sense of dread. Yes, there’s hope and the new and the unexplored. But there is also the weight of expectation. I have a couple of hundred square metres of bare earth out there waiting for me to get planting. The pressure is on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is why I’ve decided to start a new trend called &lt;strong&gt;Garden Design On a Whim&lt;/strong&gt;. Essentially, you take a group of plants that you want and organise them by some arbitary measure. I have chosen prickliness. Other people choose the colour white.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new area to fill the blank canvas is called &lt;strong&gt;Prickly Quad&lt;/strong&gt;. It will have prickly plants in it. Already, I have planted a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Crataegus+ellwangeriana&#34;&gt;Crataegus ellwangeriana&lt;/a&gt; (scarlet hawthorn) and a &lt;a href=&#34;http://pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Zanthoxylum+simulans&#34;&gt;Zanthoxylum simulans&lt;/a&gt; (Szechuan pepper). So, it is only natural to keep on the prickly tip and plant a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/plant.aspx?LatinName=Berberis+darwinii&#34;&gt;Berberis darwinii&lt;/a&gt; (Darwin’s barberry), a spikey scattering of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Mahonia+aquifolium&#34;&gt;Mahonia aquifolium&lt;/a&gt; (Oregon grape) and to crown it all, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Ribes+uva-crispa&#34;&gt;Ribes uva-crispa&lt;/a&gt; (gooseberry) &amp;lsquo;Hinnonmaki Red&amp;rsquo;. For some strange reason, I ❤️ gooseberries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But. I have reached the end of the prickly forest garden road. I wanted a &lt;a href=&#34;http://pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Viburnum+trilobum&#34;&gt;Viburnum trilobum&lt;/a&gt; (American cranberry) and &lt;em&gt;it isn’t prickly&lt;/em&gt;. And my mind is now blank on the prickle front. Time to dip in to another whimsical theme… 🙂&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dwarf comfrey ground cover planted in Shrubbery</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/dwarf-comfrey/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/dwarf-comfrey/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Symphytum ibericum (dwarf or iberian comfrey) is a good mineral accumulator ground cover for shady areas, planted buckets of the stuff today&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4700/38830083715_dacf103fc9_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dwarf comfrey in raised bed&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Symphytum ibericum in a rustic propagation bed, before being lifted, divided and planted out&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;Amidst the driving wind and hail, I planted out about 100m² of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rhs.org.uk/Plants/75444/i-Symphytum-ibericum-i/Details&#34;&gt;Symphytum ibericum&lt;/a&gt; in the Shrubbery. It’s a dwarf comfrey, about half a metre high, vigorous and spreading, which I saw in a shady spot whilst on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.agroforestry.co.uk/about_us/&#34;&gt;Martin Crawford’s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.agroforestry.co.uk/product/forest-gardening-food-forests-design-course/&#34;&gt;Forest Gardening Design Course&lt;/a&gt;. It’s known as Iberian comfrey, and from the plant range on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rhs.org.uk/Plants/75444/i-Symphytum-ibericum-i/Details&#34;&gt;RHS page&lt;/a&gt;, I think this refers to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kartli&#34;&gt;classical Iberia in Georgia&lt;/a&gt;, not the Iberian peninsula of Spain and Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought four plants from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.moorlandcottageplants.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Moorland Cottage Plants&lt;/a&gt; a year ago and popped them in a propagation bed, and they‘ve spread: big, chunky, comfrey roots going sideways and downwards. The nice thing about comfrey is that once you plant it, you have it forever. The downside is that once you plant it, you have it forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4656/39019186074_0ff6d8fca9_z_d.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Bark mulched garden area planted with ground cover&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Shrubbery is at the bottom of the slope, past the polytunnel and shaded to the south by ash trees. Ash trees, if you didn’t know, soak up water like a darned sponge. As soon as you come across the tree root network, the soil changes consistency dramatically, from a damp clay loam to a crumbly dry powder interwoven with roots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the ground preparation, I used woven plastic to sheet mulch the area for a few months, removed it and then covered the area with bark from the local sawmill, planted the shrubs and then planted the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/plant.aspx?latinname=Vinca+minor&#34;&gt;Vinca Minor&lt;/a&gt; (Lesser Periwinkle) and dwarf comfrey. The cherry on the cake is a liberal sowing of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Sinapis+alba&#34;&gt;Sinapsis alba&lt;/a&gt; (white mustard), which suppresses weed growth whilst the ground cover gets established.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, it is time to replenish the propagation beds!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4664/38830116035_43a13923ba_z_d.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Two thirds empty raised bed with comfrey&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Growing the Coppice</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/growing-the-coppice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/growing-the-coppice/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Starting the final section of the Coppice, with sweet chestnut to be planted soon&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4722/39653194582_5fda56d929_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New rows of coppice trees with two rows of sheet mulch in the foreground&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Two new rows of sheet mulch down, ready for the Castanea sativa (sweet chestnut) coppice&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;We’re very lucky to have the space to plant a coppice for our woodburners. Today was spent laying down 1 metre wide &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/Yuzet-100g-1m-wide-weed-control-fabric-ground-cover-membrane-landscape-Driveway/112634340431&#34;&gt;Yuzet woven sheet mulch&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/20-to-600-6-INCH-PLASTIC-GROUND-COVER-PEGS-FOR-FLEECE-PONDs-WEED-CONTROL/202163308968?hash=item2f11df49a8:m:mYhxW87TsxvlkIrcc5iEAaA&#34;&gt;15cm plastic ground cover pegs&lt;/a&gt;. In each section there are 3 rows, 1 metre apart, and the trees are planted 2 metres apart along the sheet mulch. Each section is 3 metres apart. Here, let me draw you a simple sketch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4764/25820536998_dbc30dc563_z_d.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sketch of coppice layout&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the top section, there’s mostly &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Alnus+glutinosa&#34;&gt;Alnus glutinosa&lt;/a&gt; (common alder), with some &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/USER/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Prunus+avium&#34;&gt;Prunus avium&lt;/a&gt; (wild cherry) thrown in the mix. The next section is a mix of Alnus glutinosa and &lt;a href=&#34;http://pfaf.org/user/plant.aspx?LatinName=Corylus+avellana&#34;&gt;Corylus avellan&lt;/a&gt; (common hazel). The third and final section, which we’re planting next week, is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/plant.aspx?LatinName=Castanea+sativa&#34;&gt;Castanea sativa&lt;/a&gt; (sweet chestnut).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alder and cherry are firewood and the hazel is for firewood and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/pea-stick&#34;&gt;pea sticks&lt;/a&gt;, whilst the chestnut is for fence posts. Apparently it is very tough wood, imported by the Romans to build roof tiles, and so is ideal for fence posts. It’ll take about 6 years to grow to the right diameter, which is about how long it takes to decompose in the ground. Symmetry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tree seedlings (whips) are easy to plant – cut a slit in the sheet mulch, use a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B000KKQW48/&#34;&gt;tree planting spade&lt;/a&gt; to dig a slit in the soil, lever a gap for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://chaosfungorum.co.uk/?product_cat=forest-garden-mix&#34;&gt;mychorizzal fungi&lt;/a&gt; coated roots, firm the slit shut and mulch the slit with cuttings.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Winter visit and forest garden plants at Colby Woodland Garden</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/colby-woodland-gardens/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/colby-woodland-gardens/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;All manner of forest garden stalwarts spotted on a winter visit to the National Trust Colby Woodland Garden near Amroth in Pembrokeshire&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4599/39541199411_24af4c796f_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bright red Cornus kousa fruit&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Lovely red Cornus kousa fruit seen on a visit to Colby Woodland Garden&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;Last weekend we paid a visit to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nationaltrust.org.uk/colby-woodland-garden&#34;&gt;Colby Woodland Garden&lt;/a&gt; in Pembrokeshire. It was damp and mild, perfect for browsing, trudging and investigating plants. I’m always struck by the variety of forest garden favourites in a ‘traditional’ garden. At Colby, there was a &lt;em&gt;vast&lt;/em&gt; number of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/plant.aspx?latinname=mahonia+aquifolium&#34;&gt;Mahonia aquifolium&lt;/a&gt; (Oregon Grapes) and other Mahonia, and my first encounter with the fruit of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/USER/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Cornus+kousa&#34;&gt;Cornus kousa&lt;/a&gt; (Japanese Dogwood)! Bright red, only slightly exaggerated by the instagrammed filter on my phone, soft and yellow inside, with a dozen seeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4626/39646072541_6dd317316f_z_d.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Cornus kousa seeds and fruit on a piece of kitchen paper&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t eat the fruit, I wasn’t too sure what it was and I thought it was a late summer rather than a winter fruit! I’ll try and propagate them (according to Martin Crawford in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.agroforestry.co.uk/product/creating-a-forest-garden-2/&#34;&gt;Creating a Forest Garden&lt;/a&gt; the seeds take 14 weeks of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thespruce.com/stratification-seeds-into-thinking-its-winter-1403100&#34;&gt;stratification&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tree/shrub itself is very elegant, we saw a fantastic specimen with beautiful cream flowers at Old Cilgwyn Gardens near Llandyfriog a couple of years ago and last year we planted a Cornus kousa var chinensis from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tyrhostrees.co.uk&#34;&gt;Ty Rhos Trees&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4642/39541113121_396afc3c3d_z_d.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Cornus kousa tree/shrub&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Near the entrance to Colby is a wall and water feature, crowned beautifully with the rampant &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/plant.aspx?LatinName=Rubus+tricolor&#34;&gt;Rubus tricolor&lt;/a&gt; (Chinese Bramble). It looked magnificent, spilling over the edge of the wall in all its evergreen glory. Don’t plant this at home kids, unless you have &lt;strong&gt;plenty&lt;/strong&gt; of space. It is so rampant it will even out compete grass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4680/24673075167_9a437c2bbf_z_d.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Evergreen vegetation spilling over wall next to steps&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, one of my favourite ground cover plants, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/plant.aspx?latinname=Vinca+minor&#34;&gt;Vinca minor&lt;/a&gt; (Lesser Periwinkle). Thick, glossy foliage, tough as old boots, a really robust and easy to care for plant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4726/39541107361_5c79571b74_z_d.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Vinca minor (Lesser Periwinkle) glossy evergreen ground cover&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversity in all things, including windbreaks</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/diversity-in-all-things/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/diversity-in-all-things/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;A mixed species north boundary windbreak hedge has grown on leaps and bounds&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4712/39615815062_b6aa7e383b_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wheelbarrow in foreground by long hedge receding to oak tree&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Replaced casualties in the North Face windbreak hedge&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;Two years ago, we planted a 90 metre windbreak hedge along the north boundary of the forest garden with a mix of four species:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=viburnum+opulus&#34;&gt;Viburnum opulus&lt;/a&gt; (Guelder Rose)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Elaeagnus+umbellata&#34;&gt;Elaegnus umbellata&lt;/a&gt; (Autumn Olive)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/User/plant.aspx?LatinName=Hippophae+rhamnoides&#34;&gt;Hippophae rhamnoides&lt;/a&gt; (Sea Buckthorn)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Amelanchier+canadensis&#34;&gt;Amelanchier canadensis&lt;/a&gt; (Juneberry)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest surprise is that the Elaegnus has done &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; badly, they’ve all pretty much died off. The Amelanchier has seen the most robust growth, now well over 2 metres high, and the Viburnum and Hippophae have done pretty well too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought that it would be the Hippophae that would struggle the most with the wet soil but no, it’s perfectly happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is strange is that a named variety of Elaegnus umbellata, &amp;lsquo;Newgate&amp;rsquo; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.agroforestry.co.uk/product/elaeagnus-umbellata-newgate/&#34;&gt;Agroforestry Trust&lt;/a&gt; which is just a bit further down the field has done really well – vibrant green shiny foliage and plenty of growth. Indeed, I’ve taken quite a few cuttings from it last autumn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst removing tree protectors and replanting the gaps with Hippophae rhamnoides, this idea of diversity is the one that really struck home. I had considered planting all Elaegnus umbellata, and I’m very glad I didn’t. The other idea is that Amelanchier seem do well, so I’ve planted an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ashwoodnurseries.com/shop/amelanchier-alnifolia-obelisk.html&#34;&gt;Amelanchier alnifolia &amp;lsquo;Obelisk&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other thing about maintenance work is that you notice yet more maintenance work: the gap between the hedge and the fence needs mulching, and some fence posts need replacing!&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Even in the smallest moments</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/even-in-the-smallest-moments/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/even-in-the-smallest-moments/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;No matter how much administration there is in the world, I try to find some time to garden&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4628/39572886252_e80df217e9_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bark mulch covered area, bamboo markers, faint line of ground lime&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Using ground lime to mark the edge of an Aronia hedge&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;Today was filled with filling in a tax return, the UK deadline looming only days away. I managed to get out into the forest garden for about &lt;strong&gt;10 minutes&lt;/strong&gt;, marking out a hedge with ground lime. Oh, sweet blesséd relief. Even 10 minutes away from the desk and the frantic tap-tapping, list checking and administrating was so worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Shrubbery (did I mention I have no head for creative names?) has had a layer of bark mulch diligently strewn upon its surface and I have started marking up the position of the shrubs. It’s a bit of a tricky situation, a big ash at the bottom of the south-facing slope, so some dry shade to watch out for. I’ll be planting &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rhs.org.uk/plants/details?plantid=1894&#34;&gt;Symphytum ibericum&lt;/a&gt; (Iberian dwarf comfrey) as a ground cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4655/39553494812_62944b3803_z_d.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Bark mulched area with bamboo markers&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Higher up, there’ll be some red and whitecurrants &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Ribes+rubrum&#34;&gt;Ribes rubrum&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rhs.org.uk/Plants/116982/Ribes-rubrum-Versailles-Blanche-(W-C)/Details&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Versailles&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rhs.org.uk/plants/details?plantid=5797&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Jonkheer Van Tets&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;), a couple of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Chaenomeles+japonica&#34;&gt;Chaenomeles japonica&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://pfaf.org/User/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Zanthoxylum+schinifolium&#34;&gt;Zanthoxylum schinifolium&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&#34;http://pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Cephalotaxus+harringtonia&#34;&gt;Cephalotaxus Harringtonia&lt;/a&gt;. With a couple of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Tilia+cordata&#34;&gt;lime trees&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=morus+alba&#34;&gt;white mulberry&lt;/a&gt; as coppiced leaf crops at the top, there isn’t much space for anything elase&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.qcad.org/en/&#34;&gt;QCAD&lt;/a&gt; for my planning but it is obvious that &lt;strong&gt;the map is not the territory&lt;/strong&gt;. The Ordnance Survey map is a few metres out, so I use it more as a &lt;em&gt;guide&lt;/em&gt; and less as an &lt;em&gt;instruction&lt;/em&gt;. Out in the field, I’m using bits of bamboo and a bucket of ground lime to mark out the circumference of the plants. Together with windbreaks, rabbit fencing, soil preparation and mulching, correct spacing is up there in the Top 5 List of Things To Consider.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tray cupboard from the dump!</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/tray-cupboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/tray-cupboard/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Picked up a freebie old chipboard cupboard from the dump, working fantastically as a tray cupboard. &#43;1 recycling&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4595/39529628612_2b91a56eeb_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Old knackered cupboard with open doors&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Sometimes the freebie ones are the best&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;After a family outing to the local dump, I managed to pick up an almost completely knackered cupboard. It’s a bit ragged around the edges but perfect for holding a stack of trays.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Misty valley whilst releasing mouse</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/misty-valley/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/misty-valley/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Not exactly forest gardening but it was lovely and misty this morning in the hills where I released the mouse&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4730/38558978625_c4c844e857_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Path through misty trees&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Path through misty trees&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;Out on a walk to release the humanely caught mouse into the cold, cold woodland up the road, and the mist was all up and about the trees yet with blue sky above. Quite enchanting.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unglamorous grunt work</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/unglamorous-grunt-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/unglamorous-grunt-work/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;In a garden, it’s 95% perspiration and 5% inspiration&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4725/38665529034_dd03ba2fba_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A mound of bark&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;It’s not the most glamorous of photographs but then a lot of gardening is about the grunt work&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;I’ve just done some calculations for our one acre forest garden. We’ve planted the canopy layer and windbreaks, sheet mulched large swathes and are now planting the shrub and ground cover layers. There’s stil 950m² to go, and I’ve worked out that‘s about &lt;strong&gt;170 hours&lt;/strong&gt; of hard graft. Most of it is hard, repetitive work – wheeling barrow after barrow of bark to mulch the newly revealed brown spongey soil; desnagging recalcitrant ground pegs from the woven plastic sheet mulch; planting dozens of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/plant.aspx?latinname=Vinca+minor&#34;&gt;Vinca minor&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rhs.org.uk/plants/details?plantid=1894&#34;&gt;Symphytum ibericum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar amount of work has gone on behind the scenes with the website: hopefully now, the blog posts are automatically published to our &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/forestgdnwales&#34;&gt;@ForestGdnWales&lt;/a&gt; Twitter page and our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/forestgardenwales/&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;. To follow, there will be more automatic publishing to other social networks, all from the comfort of our own website.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rootstock reference</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/rootstock-reference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/rootstock-reference/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Quick reference for fruiting tree rootstocks&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4636/24453546047_966ab79f99_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration comparing different rootstock heights in relation to person&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Rootstocks explained illustration, I think from Johnstown Garden Centre&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;This is the best &lt;a href=&#34;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4636/24453546047_3e5fb2dfec_o_d.png&#34;&gt;rootstock diagram&lt;/a&gt; that I’ve found, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.johnstowngardencentre.ie/blog/johnstowngardencentre.ie/2016/03/08/rootstocks-explained/&#34;&gt;Johnstown Garden Centre&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very dwarf &lt;em&gt;1.5m-2m&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple: &lt;strong&gt;M27&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dwarf &lt;em&gt;1.8m-2.5m&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple: &lt;strong&gt;M9&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pear: &lt;strong&gt;Quince C&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cherry: &lt;strong&gt;Gisela 5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Semi dwarf &lt;em&gt;2.2m-3m&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple: &lt;strong&gt;M26&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apricot: &lt;strong&gt;Torinel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plum: &lt;strong&gt;Pixy, VVA-1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Medium &lt;em&gt;2.5m-4m&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple: &lt;strong&gt;M116&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Semi-vigorous &lt;em&gt;2.5m-4.5m&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple: &lt;strong&gt;MM106&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pear: &lt;strong&gt;Quince A&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plum: &lt;strong&gt;St Julien A&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cherry: &lt;strong&gt;Colt&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vigorous &lt;em&gt;3.5m-4.5m&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple: &lt;strong&gt;MM111&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pear: &lt;strong&gt;Pyrodwarf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very vigorous &lt;em&gt;4.5m+&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple: &lt;strong&gt;M25&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pear: &lt;strong&gt;Pyrus communis&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Pyrus Kirchensaller&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cherry: &lt;strong&gt;F.12.1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plum: &lt;strong&gt;Brompton&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Planting &amp; Pruning workshop notes</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/planting-pruning-workshop-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/planting-pruning-workshop-notes/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Scant notes from the Planting &amp; Pruning workshop held by The People’s Orchard in St Dogmaels on 7th December 2017&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4587/38517307965_1f502a7949_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fruit and growth buds on apple tree&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Martin Hayes, Consultant Orchardist, planting trees with The People’s Orchard project, St Dogmaels&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;On 7th December, I had the good fortune to attend a free Planting &amp;amp; Pruning workshop, held by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stdogmaelsabbey.org.uk/peoplesorchard&#34;&gt;The People’s Orchard&lt;/a&gt; based &lt;a href=&#34;http://stdogmaelsabbey.org.uk/&#34;&gt;St Dogmaels Abbey&lt;/a&gt;. It was run by Martin Hayes, an orchardist who works regularly for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://glosorchards.org/home/&#34;&gt;Gloucestershire Orchard Trust&lt;/a&gt;, together with Nia and Sophie from The People’s Orchard. Martin was fantastic, as good with people as with trees, and I learnt a vast amount together with a dozen other volunteers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a beginner in everything, I made scribbly notes between wielding secateurs and taking documentary photos. What follows really is aide de memoire tamis for my own benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a little &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forestgarden.wales/rootstock-reference/&#34;&gt;rootstock reference&lt;/a&gt; which is handy. Different highly bred fruit (eg apples, pears, plums, cherries etc) are grafted on to different rootstock, which determines their vitality and thus height and diameter. I learned that the apple rootstocks MM106 (4m) &amp;amp; M25 (4.5m+) don’t need staking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also learnt that you can use &lt;a href=&#34;https://duckduckgo.com/?q=single+core+electric+wire&amp;amp;t=ffab&amp;amp;iax=images&amp;amp;ia=images&#34;&gt;single core electric cable&lt;/a&gt; to tie the trees to the stake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4735/39316408421_38ecdbb4b7_o_d.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Illustration of how to tie tree to stake with figure of 8 electric cable&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Figure of 8 for tying tree to stake&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another handy tip was that it &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; make a difference planting the lead root &lt;strong&gt;windward&lt;/strong&gt;, ie plant the biggest pointy root toward the prevailing wind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4738/25447923018_cfa5317121_o_d.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Plant the lead root _toward_ the direction of the prevailing wind&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other tips include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Never&lt;/strong&gt; let the roots dry out when you’re planting. Put them in water if need be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iansturrockandsons.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Ian Sturrock &amp;amp; Sons&lt;/a&gt; is a very good fruit tree nursery in Bangor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s not always necessary to water trees in if the soil is very damp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rule of thumb: cut 1/3 off, no more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always cut to a bud or a branch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prune the tree to reclaim the centre line ie where the central trunk should be&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Balance the tree by taking off top-heavy, lop-sided branches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prune from the centre, not the edges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Water shoots are the new vertical shoots which grow in response to pruning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bramley particularly vigorous, leave water shoots for upward growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time scale for pruning:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First year water shoots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second year bud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Third year fruit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest takeaway from the day is to &lt;strong&gt;think of the pressure of the sap rising&lt;/strong&gt;. A tree wants to grow, you just (sic) need to encourage it in the right direction. You may need to leave water shoots where you want the growth, or you may leave a dog-leg shaped shoot, to divert the growth elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you don’t want is &lt;strong&gt;lollipopped tree&lt;/strong&gt;. This is where pruning done in a circle around the &lt;em&gt;edge&lt;/em&gt; of the tree. This encourages shoots at the end of the branches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Omissions, opinions, outrage? Tweet me &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/forestgdnwales&#34;&gt;@ForestGdnWales&lt;/a&gt; 🙂&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predator strip!</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/predator-strip/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/predator-strip/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Martin Crawford’s predator strip is a combination of perennial flowering plants to attract predatory and pollinating insects&lt;/p&gt;
        
          &lt;figure&gt;
            &lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4686/38350635275_7000be4a15_z_d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bright yellow flower on evergreen plant&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;Brachyglottis &#39;Senecio&#39; in flower&lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;On the longest night in the depths of winter, with temperatures plummeting to 10°C, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ow.ly/u9rm30hrbpU&#34;&gt;Brachyglottis (Dunedin Group) &amp;lsquo;Sunshine&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt; is flowering! Along with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/plant.aspx?LatinName=Myrrhis+odorata&#34;&gt;Myrrhis odorata (Sweet Cicely)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pfaf.org/user/Plant.aspx?LatinName=Filipendula+ulmaria&#34;&gt;Filipendula ulmaria (Meadowsweet)&lt;/a&gt;, it forms part of a “predator strip” by the raised beds, to encourage predatory and pollinating insects, like &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoverfly&#34;&gt;hoverflies&lt;/a&gt;. I heard about them on Martin Crawford’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.agroforestry.co.uk/product/forest-gardening-food-forests-design-course/&#34;&gt;Forest Gardening Design Course&lt;/a&gt; in 2016 and I’m really pleased to have finally planted my own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is that Brachyglottis &amp;lsquo;Sunshine&amp;rsquo; (previously known as Senecio) is as tough as nails, used in countless car parks and municipal spaces. I say almost, I managed to inadverntently dispatch one. Sweet Cicely is also supposedly easy to grow, though again, I couldn’t get the seeds to germinate and ended up buying them in a boot sale from the local garden centre. Meadowsweet thankfully grows like a weed. I like weeds.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to Forest Garden Wales website!</title>
      <link>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/welcome-to-forest-garden-wales-website/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>helo@forestgarden.wales (Jake Rayson)</author>
      <guid>https://www.forestgarden.wales/blog/welcome-to-forest-garden-wales-website/</guid>
      <description>
        &lt;p class="p-summary"&gt;Forest Garden Wales has a website&lt;/p&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;Welcome to our new website, built by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.growdigital.org/&#34;&gt;Grow Digital&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like a garden, there is always plenty to do and we will be rolling out our new design soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018, you should be able to buy our video forest garden courses online as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find us on social media in these different places:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ForestGdnWales&#34;&gt;@ForestGdnWales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facebook &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/Forest-Garden-Wales/&#34;&gt;www.facebook.com/Forest-Garden-Wales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/111290684473488016210&#34;&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
